<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An antidote against popery confected out of scriptures, fathers, councels, and histories. Wherein dialogue-wise are shewed, the points, grounds, and antiquitie of the Protestant religion; and the first springing vp of the points of popery: together with the Antichristianisme thereof. Being alone sufficient to inable any Protestant of meane capacitie, to vnderstand and yeeld a reason of his religion, and to incounter with and foyle the aduersary. By Iohn Mayer, B.D. and pastor of the Church of little Wratting in Suffolke.</title>
            <author>Mayer, John, 1583-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 231 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07344</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17729</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102861</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838623</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838623</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3008</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07344)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3008)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1146:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An antidote against popery confected out of scriptures, fathers, councels, and histories. Wherein dialogue-wise are shewed, the points, grounds, and antiquitie of the Protestant religion; and the first springing vp of the points of popery: together with the Antichristianisme thereof. Being alone sufficient to inable any Protestant of meane capacitie, to vnderstand and yeeld a reason of his religion, and to incounter with and foyle the aduersary. By Iohn Mayer, B.D. and pastor of the Church of little Wratting in Suffolke.</title>
                  <author>Mayer, John, 1583-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 81, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. F[lesher] for Iohn Grismand: and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Alley, at the signe of the Gunne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3008:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3008:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANTIDOTE AGAINST POPERY: Confected out of Scriptures, Fathers, Councels, and Hiſtories.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN DIALOGVE-wiſe are ſhewed, the points, grounds, and antiquitie of the Proteſtant Religion; and the firſt ſpringing vp of the points of Popery: together with the Antichriſtianiſme thereof.</p>
            <p>Being alone ſufficient to inable any Proteſtant of meane capacitie, to vnderſtand and yeeld a reaſon of his Religion, and to incounter with and foyle the Aduerſary.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Iohn Mayer,</hi> B. D. and Paſtor of the Church of little Wratting in <hi>Suffolke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. F.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Griſmand:</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Alley, at the ſigne of the Gunne. 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3008:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3008:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY <hi>JAMES,</hi> BY THE grace of God, King of Great <hi>Britaine, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dread Soueraigne:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that I had compiled this enſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing Dialogue, I thought your Maieſtie the moſt fit <hi>Maecenas</hi> for it; both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the matter and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. The matter is a Diſpute about Religion, both Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and Popiſh; the manner is by vſurping certaine names occurring in the <hi>Acts of the holy Apoſtles,</hi> and accommodating them ſo, as
<pb facs="tcp:3008:3"/>may beſt befit theſe times: amongſt which, the chiefe is <hi>Sergius Paulus,</hi> before whom <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Ely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> enter the liſts, with an ayme chiefely at the ouercomming of this honourable perſon. The iſſue is, according to <hi>Pauls</hi> deſire, the ſetling of <hi>Sergi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Paulus</hi> in the truth; ſo that with him there was no more place now for <hi>Elymas.</hi> Your Maieſtie hath beene much conuerſant in diſputations, and now at length, I vvill not ſay being ſetled (for it appeareth ſufficiently, that there hath euer been a ſetledneſſe and reſolution in your Royall breſt) but not thinking good to lend an eare any longer to the friuolous arguments of ſuch as haue ſought your auerſion from the Truth, your MAIESTIE hath prouided, that they ſhall haue no more <hi>copĭe of diſputing</hi> within your whole iuriſdiction. The Worke, I confeſſe, is too ſleighty to bee preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before ſo large an vnderſtanding, and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor too meane to preſume to ſo high a patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage:<note place="margin">Epiſtle Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory vpon the Lords Prayer.</note> But foraſmuch as your Maieſtie hath ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged it to haue beene your owne courſe to dedicate your royall writings to fit perſons, with whom each Tract might beſt ſuite; my hope is, that my boldneſſe ſhall haue pardon, if in follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo worthy an example, I haue aſpired to this dedication. It hath bred much ſollicitude in your Maieſtie (as your late directions touching prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and preaching doe teſtifie) to conſider the dayly increaſe of Popiſh ſuperſtition euen within your Maieſties Dominions. And wee your faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſubiects cannot but haue a ſympathy herein; for which cauſe wee highly applauding that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb facs="tcp:3008:3"/>of inſtructing in the Principles of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, doe apply our ſelues diligently to this Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheticall kinde of teaching, if haply the <hi>mobile vulgus</hi> might thus bee faſter grounded. And for mine owne part, according to that ſlender skill, which GOD hath giuen mee, I haue by vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting endeauoured to further this kinde of teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">Engliſh Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme.</note> and to hold to the patterne of the leſſer au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized Catechiſme, for the auoiding of confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by an vniforme proceeding: wherein I haue not beene altogether fruſtrated of my end neither, there being many Reuerend Diuines and others, amongſt whom this labour of mine hath beene ſo accepted, as that it hath long agoe come to the third impreſſion. Now if my coniecture deceiue mee not, another good helpe to preſerue from this infection, would bee ſome Antidote of our te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents and grounds, and of Popiſh tenents and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices in the worſhip of God, without all ground ſet vp, either by aduantage taken of the darkneſſe, or by force, there beeing none able to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance in ſeuerall times and ages of the world; eſpecially if it might bee perſpicuous and plaine to any capacitie, and briefe for euery ones leiſure and abilitie. And ſuch is this, which I here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto your Sacred Maieſtie, the which or the like vnto which, I could wiſh that euery one, who is not furniſhed with better, would make his <hi>vade mecum.</hi> That Reuerend and learned Biſhop of <hi>Meath</hi> hath lately put out a Worke in anſwere to a Ieſuite, of the noueltie of Poperie, in ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete a manner, as that a man would thinke, as
<pb facs="tcp:3008:4"/>it was ſaid of the anſwer of our bleſſed Sauiour, none ſhould dare to aske that queſtion any more. If this of mine comming after, it ſhould ſeeme ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, my apologie is, that our Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the greater hath alſo the leſſer Catechiſme. Babes muſt haue their prouiſion as well as thoſe that are ſtronger. Your Maieſties care of the good of this Church committed vnto you herein, like to that of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> in the matter of Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ianiſme, as it hath much reioyced my heart, and the hearts of many thouſands that pray for the proſperitie of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo it hath incouraged mee to preſſe into your Sacred preſence with this my Goates-haire, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to bring better. Your Maieſtie, I know, hath no need of ſuch Tracts, but many of vs that bring preſents in this kinde may bee glad to learne from your Pen, and to receiue knowledge from your lips; yea,<note place="margin">1 King. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>bleſſed are they that ſtand alwayes in thy preſence to heare thy wiſedome.</hi> Yet vouchſafe, I beſeech your Maieſtie, to ſuffer it to paſſe vnder the protection of your countenance to your people, and I doubt not, but the Proteſtant Religion ſhall hereby ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vnto them as it is, ſo amiable and rightly grounded; and the Religion of the Church of Rome ſo corrupt, and peruerting the grounds, as that thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, which ſhall attentiuely and without preiudice reade it, ſhall herein bleſſe God for you; ſome that were ignorant of the differences of theſe religions, and ſo ſtanding indifferently affected, being better informed; ſome that were wauering through the ſeeming truth of that hereſie, being confirmed; and ſome that were ſimply ſeduced and gone from vs,
<pb facs="tcp:3008:4"/>being againe to the truth reduced, to the great glory of God, and to the fulfilling of the number of moſt loyall and faithfull ſubiects, in whom the heart of your Maieſty may moſt ſafely truſt. The Father of lights, who hath ſo enlightned your knowledge; the Son, that life, who hath ſo viuified your heart; and the Spirit, that ſire, who hath ſo inflamed your zeale for the truth, increaſe, confirme and proſper this your knowledge, life, and zeale to the benefiting of many ſoules, and to the ioyfull giuing vp of your Maieſties Accounts at the great day of reckoning; Amen prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Maieſties moſt</hi> humbly deuoted <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect and ſeruant,</hi> IOHN MAYER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3008:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3008:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To all that conſcionably inquire after</hi> the Truth, that they may be ſaued; both of the reformed Religion, and of the Romane Catholike.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, thou mayeſt haply blame mee for my ouer-diligence in writing-ſo much, and now vpon a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect ſo throughly canuaſed already in diuers bookes of learned Authors. But know, that I haue beene drawne to doe this by the ſollicitation of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, being l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th of my ſelfe to interrupt my courſe in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tract, which I haue begung,<note place="margin">Treaſury of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ-expoſitions.</note> and to perfect which will require the whole life and labour. of one whole man. Many haue written ſo I grant, in this argument, as that they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed this of mine without all compare: but ſome are ſo large and haue made their bookes to ſwell to ſo great volumes, as that they are onely for profeſſed Students, and not for euery mans memory, leyfure or money. Some againe are ſo ſhort, and doe ſo proſecute ſome points onely, as that howſoeuer they be for euery man, yet when they are read, almoſt euery man remaineth ſtill vnſatisfied in many things. Laſtly, ſome are neither too large, nor too ſhort, but haue written fully, methodically, and logically: yet not ſo fully, but that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers particulars haue beene omitted, the common motiues on both ſides haue not beene ſo throughly weighed, the originalls of the many e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rours of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Apoſtolike Antiquity of the Reformed Religion hath not beene ſo declared, nor the treatiſes in the manner of them ſo fitted to the capacity of the vulgar, ſo as that many read them, but for want of capacity, and through theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects
<pb facs="tcp:3008:6"/>in the worke, are not ſo much moued. Now to ſupply all theſe defects, and to inſtruct all, euen my moſt vncapable Country-men in euery point and motiue, ſo as that there might be nothing to hinder thoſe that deſire to know the truth, and to cleaue vnto and obey it; I haue written this plaine and ſhort Dialogue. And herein I am not ſo blind but I ſee to what enuying and hard cenſuring I expoſe my ſelfe, but neither credit, nor life are any thing to me, ſo that by any meanes I may ſaue ſome: Onely let mee ſay thus much in way of Apologie, that it is well knowne, that I am not malicious againſt the Romane Catholikes, nor out of ſpite haue thus written or vſed the name of <hi>Elymas</hi> to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace any but wilfull Pontificians, who for ſiniſter reſpects, againſt their knowledge ſeeke to lead into error not onely common people, but noble gouernors, that attentiuely hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching. For the reſt let mee intreat you to read me, not as an enemy, vnleſſe I ſhall therefore bee coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted your enemy,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe I tell you the truth;</hi> but as one that deſireth and prayeth for your ſaluation; and I doubt not, but through Gods grace, you ſhall ſee that, which will make you ſuſpect, and not ſo well to like your preſent eſtate, nor ſo much to condemne our reformation, if not to ſeparate your ſelues, and to come out with vs from amongſt them, leſt ye periſh euerlaſtingly. For I profeſſe before God, who knoweth all ſecrets, that till I ſeriouſly ſtudied vpon theſe things, I was not ſo reſolued, that the Pope is the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, nor your tenents and ſuperſtitions ſo damnable: but the further I waded into this ſtudy, the more was I reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, ſo as that now I make no further doubt of it. And therefore my hope is, that the like effect may by reading theſe my meditations bee wrought in others alſo, that the vnſtable may be ſetled, and the erring bee brought home into the one ſheepfold of Chriſt, before it be too late, which God grant vnto you all for his mercies ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:3008:6"/>
            <head>A Table of the points of both <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions diſcuſſed in this Booke.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>Of the Proteſtant Religion.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> God onely is to be beleeued in, and not the Church. <hi>Page. 2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> Chriſt onely is our Mediator, and not the Saints departed. <hi>Page. 2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> Iuſtification and ſaluation is by faith onely. <hi>Page. 3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> Faith aſſureth of ſaluation. <hi>Page. 4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> The ſoules of the faithfull goe not to Purgatory. <hi>Page. 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> Prayers for the dead auaile not. <hi>Page. 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> The Sacrament of the Lords Supper is no ſacrifice.</item>
               <item>There is no reall preſence, it ought to be in both kinds. <hi>Page. 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8</hi> Baptiſme doth not quite: ake away naturall corruption. <hi>Page. 7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9</hi> The Sacraments of the new Teſtament are but two onely. <hi>Page. 7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10</hi> There is no perfection of righteouſneſſe in this life. <hi>Page. 7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11</hi> There is no liberty of will vnto good. <hi>Page. 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12</hi> Mariage is free for all men. <hi>Page. 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13</hi> The Scriptures alone are ſufficient. <hi>Page. 10</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14</hi> None ought to be debarred from reading the Scriptures. <hi>Page. 11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15</hi> The Pope is not ſupreme head of the Church. <hi>Page. 12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16</hi> God onely is to be called vpon, and not the Saints departed. <hi>Page. 14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17</hi> The vſe of images in diuine worſhip is vnlawfull <hi>Page. 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18</hi> All prayers ought to be in a knowne tongue <hi>Page. 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>19</hi> Confeſſion of ſinnes is not neceſſary to any but to God onely. <hi>Page. 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>20</hi> Satisfaction for ſinne cannot be made by workes of penance. <hi>Page. 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>21</hi> All ſinnes are mort all none veniall. <hi>Page. 18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>22</hi> To goe on Pilgimage is a ſuperſtition. <hi>Page. 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>23</hi> Extreme vncton ought not now to be. <hi>Page. 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>24</hi> Croſſing and holy water are vaine ſuperſtitions. <hi>Page. 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>25</hi> Nothing is to be taken from the word for any end. <hi>Page. 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>26</hi> Wilfull pouerty is not warrantable. <hi>Page. 20</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3008:7"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>27</hi> To vow perpetuall <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irginity is vnlawfull. <hi>page. 21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>28</hi> Of Holy dayes and faſts vpon their Eeues. <hi>page. 21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>29</hi> The Clergy is ſubiect to the King, as well as the laity. <hi>page. 22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>30</hi> Superſtitions ceremonies in baptizing, are anoyded. <hi>page. 23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>31</hi> The holy S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rament is not to be kept for after-vſes. <hi>page. 23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>32</hi> The Church of Rome is no true Church, becauſe ſhe razeth the foundation. <hi>page. 24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>33</hi> The ignorant Papiſts indangered as well as others. <hi>page. 32</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Of Popery.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> Satisfaction for temporall puniſhments. <hi>page. 25</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> The merit of Saints: of the Maſſe, and of workes. <hi>page. 26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> The ſaints Mediators. <hi>page. 27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> Free-will preparing for grace. <hi>page. 28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>By theſe the foundation is razed. <hi>page. 29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> Vncertainty of faith. <hi>page. 31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> The Popes ſupremacy. <hi>page. 37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> The worſhipping of Images. <hi>page. 43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8</hi> The ſingle life of Prieſts. <hi>page. 47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9</hi> The reall preſence. <hi>page. 49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10</hi> Prayers in the Latine tongue. <hi>page. 53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11</hi> Purgatory and praying for the dead. <hi>page. 54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12</hi> Croſſing and holy water. <hi>page. 55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13</hi> Freewill. <hi>page. 59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14</hi> Iuſtification by workes. <hi>page. 60</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15</hi> The vncertainty of ſaluation. <hi>page. 62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16</hi> Satisfaction for ſinne. <hi>page. 62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17</hi> Seuen Sacraments. <hi>page. 64</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18</hi> Apocryphall Scriptures and traditions, &amp;c. <hi>page. 65</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3008:7"/>
            <head>AN ANTIDOTE AGAINST POPERY.</head>
            <head type="sub">In way of a Dialogue: <hi>Wherein,</hi> The Speakers are <hi>Saul</hi> or <hi>Paul, Sergius Paulus,</hi> and <hi>Elymas.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Oble Sir, becauſe you are an elect veſſell, the Lord hath ſent mee to publiſh the true Religion vnto you, by the imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and right profeſſing whereof you may be ſaued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sergius Paulus.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is that religion?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>It is the Chriſtian Religion; taught, and maintained in the reformed, or Proteſtant Churches.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherein ſtandeth this religion?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>The maine points of it concerne either faith, or practice in exerciſing the parts of Gods worſhip.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Concerning faith, what doth the Proteſtant Church hold?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>I will not rehearſe all contained in the Symboll or Creed of the Apoſtles, about which it is agreed by all that beare the name of Chriſtians; but onely thoſe particulars, about which there is difference.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:3008:8"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am alſo reſolued by that which I haue heard from thee heretofore, of all that is generally held by all Chriſtians, that there is one God, which made, and gouerneth the whole world, who is a ſpirit, incomprehenſible, and comprehending all things: and one Lord Ieſus Chriſt, perfect God, and perfect Man, who dyed for our ſinnes, &amp;c. Tell me therefore onely, what particular points of faith are held by the Proteſtants, but contradicted by others?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>The firſt is, that God onely is to be beleeued in, and not any man of what title or ſucceſſion ſo euer, nor yet any company of men called the Church:<note place="margin">Rom. 3.4.</note> becauſe <hi>God only is true and all men are lyers:</hi> neither doth the Apoſtles Creed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound any other to beleeued in but God onely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What, doe you ſay that the Church is not to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued in? Is it not expreſſely ſaid, I beleeue in the holy Catholike Church?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>It is indeed ſaid I beleeue the holy Catholike Church, but not in it; becauſe the Catholike Church, that is, the Church of God being in all ages, and ouer-ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all parts of the world, is an obiect of faith, and not of ſenſe; foraſmuch as by ſenſe and experience wee cannot know this, but by faith onely, as wee apprehend the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints, forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and the life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. Of all which the ſame is ſaid that of the Catholike Church, ſeeing there is but one Verbe, <hi>I beleeue,</hi> after which they all follow. So that if hence it might bee gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the Church is to bee beleeued in, it may likewiſe be gathered, that the remiſſion of ſinnes, and the refurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the body, &amp;c. are to bee beleeued in, which vvere ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the ſecond particular point?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>The ſecond is, that Chriſt Ieſus is our onely Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and Aduocate with the Father in Heauen; neither is it lawfull to come to the Father by any other but by him, and in his name alone: and that the Saints departed out of this life know not of our ſeeking their mediation, if wee ſhould craue it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is the Lord ſo ſtrict, that by him wee are thus reſtrained from all Mediators in Heauen, and yet directeth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3008:8"/>vs to craue the helpe of others vpon earth to pray for vs?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>It is the voice of Gods own Spirit. <hi>There is one God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.5.</note> 
                  <hi>and one Mediator betwixt God and Man,</hi> of whom onely, and of none elſe mention is made ſundry times; as <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16 <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. As for that direction to craue the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of men vpon earth, it is that by hauing mutuall help one from another, our mutuall loue might increaſe, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be in crauing their mediation in Heauen, ſeeing how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer our loue may increaſe towards them, yet theirs is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready fully perfect. But to inſiſt vpon nothing elſe, they cannot heare vs, as the liuing doe; and if they heare, it is kept ſecret from vs: neither hath the Lord ſpoken one word to direct vs to them, without which, who ſo ſeeketh to them, may iuſtly haue the complaint taken vp againſt him,<note place="margin">Ier, 14.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee runneth before he is ſent.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the third particular point?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>The third is, that we are iuſtified and ſaued only by faith in Ieſus Chriſt, and that our workes euen when we are at the beſt, merit nothing towards our eternall glorification. For to this effect ſpeaketh the Lord.<note place="margin">Luke 17.10.</note> 
                  <hi>When yee haue done all that ye can, ſay that yee are vnprofitable ſeruants.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul. A man is iuſtified by faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 3.28.</note> 
                  <hi>without the workes of the Law.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is not the worke of him that hath faith then of more vertue, then his that hath none? Is he not Chriſts member, and ſo Chriſts vertue his vertue, that as in Chriſts actions, ſo in his there ſhould be merit.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>The workes of the beſt are of no more vertue to merit, becauſe hee is ſtill a ſeruant, and bound in duty to what hee doth, whereas merit implyeth doing more then duty requireth. And as for Chriſts vertue communicated vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, it is ſufficient, that he is made thus worthy, though not his works, ſeeing perfect bleſſedneſſe is already fully me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited by Chriſt for him, neither is there need of any more merit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Can hee be ſaid to be iuſtified then that hath no workes, but reſteth vpon a bare faith?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>No by no meanes: for faith which iuſtifieth, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3008:9"/>by loue, is liuely by workes, as the bodie by the ſoule. Wherefore Saint <hi>Iames</hi> writing againſt ſuch a faith as is without workes,<note place="margin">Iam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.24.</note> ſaith; <hi>A man is not iuſtified by faith onely, but by the workes of the Law:</hi> That is, hee is not become iuſt and righteous in the ſight of God, that hath a ſingle and bare faith, but proueth his faith ſound by his workes. For, that he diſputeth not of faith, which is the ſauing grace wrought in the hearts of the Elect; but of a common faith of which euen Deuils are capable, is plaine from the Text. For onely that common faith is the faith, of which he ſaith, <hi>A man is not iuſtified by faith onely.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the fourth particular point?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>The fourth is, that faith aſſureth a man without wauering or doubting of the remiſſion of his ſinnes, and of eternall ſaluation.<note place="margin">Rom. 4.20.</note> For ſuch was <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith. <hi>Hee doubted not through vnbeliefe, but ſtrengthened himſelf in faith.</hi> And that faith which is ioyned with wauering in any man <hi>is like the waues of the Sea.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 1.6.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is much that man ſhould come to know ſo farre what the will of God is, touching his future eſtate. It may be that ſome ſingular man as</hi> Abraham <hi>or the holy Apoſtles, might ſurely know by reuelation, becauſe they had more then ordinary acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with God: but for other beleeuers I cannot ſee, how they ſhould know, though they may all hope well.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>There is great reaſon, why any faithfull perſon ſhould know this, becauſe hee hath receiued the Spirit of God,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.12.</note> 
                  <hi>which knoweth Gods will,</hi> euen as the ſpirit within a man knoweth his minde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But ſeeing euery man is apt to conceiue the beſt of himſelfe, and naturall preſumption ofttimes aſſureth a man of his ſaluation; how ſhall he know that it is the ſpirit, whereby hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be thus aſſured, and not his owne partiall fantaſie?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>It is a great indignitie to the Lord, when as he hath taught vs,<note place="margin">Rom 8.16.</note> that his <hi>Spirit witneſſeth with our ſpirits that we are the children of God;</hi> to queſtion whether this teſtimonie can be knowne: for wherefore ſerueth the teſtimonie of any, if it be vnknowne. Many indeed doe through their own fault deceiue themſelues, becauſe being void of the ſpirit of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3008:9"/>ſanctification they preſume: But hee that is renued in his mind vnto holineſſe, can neuer be deceiued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Will the Spirit alwayes abide where once he hath ſanctified? or may not a relapſe to carnality and ſinne, cauſe him to depart, that ſo the eſtate of that man, who hath beene once ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, through his owne default, may become as damnable or more damnable then before? which if it may happen to be ſo, what certainty can any man haue?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>He that is borne of God ſinneth not, neither can be,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Iohn 3.9.</note> 
                  <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is borne of God.</hi> If I haue ſeemed to ſpeake other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of thoſe that <hi>haue beene enlightned and made partakers of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 6.6.</note> I ſayd it to ſtirre vp to worke out ſaluation with feare and trembling, and not as poſitiuely ſetting down that ſuch might fall away. Wherefore I added, <hi>I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded better things of you, and ſuch as accompany ſaluation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 6.9.</note> 
                  <hi>for God is not vnfaithfull to forget your labour and worke in the Lord.</hi> And, <hi>he that hath begun this good worke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 1.6.</note> 
                  <hi>will perfect is in you.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the fift particular point?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>The fift is, That the ſoules of the faithfull being iuſtified by Chriſt, doe immediately after their departure out of their bodies, take poſſeſſion of that inheritance which he hath by his blood purchaſed for them; and that there is not any puniſhment by a Purgatory fire to bee fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther endured before their comming into heauen.<note place="margin">Luke 12.</note> For <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> was caried immediately into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome; and the dead that dye in the Lord are ſaid to be bleſſed, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they reſt from their labours:</hi> which were not true,<note place="margin">Reu. 14.13.</note> if they had more miſery yet to paſſe through, rather greater then any already paſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But then thy ſelfe haſt taught,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.11.</note> 
                  <hi>that</hi> euery one muſt be tryed in the fire, <hi>after which, he whoſe worke abideth ſhall be rewarded.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Thou art vtterly miſtaken: for I neuer taught that euery man muſt be tryed by the fire, but euery mans worke; concerning which it may be doubted here, euen as of met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall before it commeth to the fire: but at the laſt day, which ſhall be a time of fire and burning flames, it will plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3008:10"/>what ſolid or chaffie doctrine any man hath built vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the true foundation Chriſt, becauſe the righteous Iudge of the whole world comming in perſon, will lay euery thing open as it is. They are very inconſiderate therefore that take this as ſpoken of perſons, it being altogether beſides my purpoſe there to ſpeake of any but builders, or of any paine by them to be ſuffered after death for the more clari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of them from ſinne: but onely of the difference of their acceptance before God at the laſt, as they haue beene ſolid or ſleighty in their building; that golden Doctors of the Church might be incouraged, and the chaffie terrified, as being like, if they would not build better, to come into great perill at the laſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the fixt particular point?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>The ſixt is, that when any are departed out of this life, we that ſuruiue can doe nothing auailable to their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, by offering vp any prayers, almes, or ſacrifice. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as the rich man being dead,<note place="margin">Luke 16.26.</note> it was ſaid, they <hi>that would come from thence could not:</hi> ſo we beleeue, that there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouing of ſoules from woe to bliſſe, but as the tree falleth, ſo it lyeth.<note place="margin">2 Sam 12.</note> And therefore, as <hi>Dauid</hi> prayed for his child being aliue, but when it was dead, ceaſed ſo to doe: in like manner we pray for the ſicke, as being yet capable of mercy, but if they be dead, we ceaſe from praying any more, being aſſured, that to pray now is no more deuotion, but ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſauoring more of violent affection, then of right reaſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the ſeuenth particular point?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>The ſeuenth is, that the Sacrament of the Lords Supper ought to bee adminiſtred to all the people in both kinds, and that it is a Sacrament conſiſting of two parts, the thing ſignifying, and the thing ſignified; and not a ſacrifice of Chriſts very body and blood there ſubſtantially preſent, as when he was crucified vpon the Croſſe, iterated againe by the Prieſt to as great auaile, as when he ſuffered for vs. For this were not to remember Chriſt abſent in the fleſh, but to bring him backe againe to the death tenne thouſand times ouer, and to make a miracle the obiect of faith, when as the proper end of miracles is to helpe vs to beleeue things
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3008:10"/>inuiſible, themſelues being alwayes viſible and ſenſible.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is not the Lord then to be beieeued, who ſaith,</hi> This is my body?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Yes by all meanes, but as in other ſpeeches wee muſt not looke ſo much to the letter as to the ſenſe (as when he ſaith, <hi>I am the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine, I am the Doore, I am the Way;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5.1.</note> in all which hee is figuratiue) ſo here taking the ſpeech as it is meant, we beleeue it with all our hearts, that the bread is Chriſts body to the faithfull receiuer, and is thus called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by it Chriſt is exhibited and receiued indeed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the eighth particular point?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>The eighth point is, that in Baptiſme there is true and certaine remiſſion of ſinnes to all repentant and faithfull perſons, but not an abolition of naturall corruption: for that remaineth ſtill in the baptized, <hi>to intice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 1 14. Gal. 5.17. Rom. 7.23.</note> 
                  <hi>and to draw to actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſinning,</hi> in ſo much that the regenerate <hi>cannot doe what they would,</hi> nor yet I my ſelfe, <hi>for I find in mee the law of my members rebelling againſt the law of my mind, and leading mee captiue to the law of ſinne.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the ninth particular point?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>The ninth is, that theſe two Sacraments are all the Sacraments of the New Teſtament, becauſe the Lord Ieſus ordained theſe, and none of the other fiue, which by ſome are added to make vp the number ſeuen. For a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is Gods ſeale, and ſo properly to be appointed by him, who alone hath the power ouer that which is ſealed vp hereby.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the tenth particular point?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>The tenth point is, that the beſt are not ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly righteous in this life, neither can any attaine to ſuch perfection in keeping Gods Lawes, but that they are ſtill much faulty: <hi>for in many things wee ſinne all:</hi> and,<note place="margin">Iam. 3.2. 1 Iohn 1.8.</note> 
                  <hi>If wee ſay that we haue no ſinne, we deceiue our ſelues, and there is no truth in vs.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What? doth Chriſt then command vs things im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible? for he biddeth vs</hi> be perfect,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.48. Phil. 3.15.</note> as our Father which is in heauen is perfect; <hi>and thou thy ſelfe haſt ſaid,</hi> ſo many of vs as be perfect, let vs be thus minded.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3008:11"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>There is a twofold perfection, of parts, and of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees: perfection of parts, is when a man hath not onely one grace, or a few graces, but all graces: perfection of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees is when a man hath attained ſuch a meaſure of grace, as that there is in him no imperfection or want at all. Of the former the Lord ſpeaketh, that wee ſhould loue not onely friends, but alſo enemies, and exerciſe benignitie to all, and not of the other. Againe, there is a perfection of ſinceritie, and a perfection of ſanctitie, of the former of which onely I ſpake, and not of the latter; for I had immediately before ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knwoledged my ſelfe not perfect in that ſenſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the eleuenth particular point?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>The eleuenth point is, that mans will is ſo corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted euer ſince the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> as that hee cannot deſire to be conuerted, or thinke a thought tending to conuerſion: but of his owne will, he is caried onely to euill, till that God of his grace changeth his will by putting a new heart and ſpirit into him.<note place="margin">Gen. 6.5. 2 Cor. 3.5. Phil. 2.13.</note> For, <hi>all the imaginations of mans heart are onely euill continually:</hi> and, <hi>we are not able to thinke a good thought as of our ſelues,</hi> but <hi>it is God that worketh in vs the will and the deed of his owne good pleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why then are we bidden to turne from ſinne, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and beleeue the Goſpell? and why is it vſed as an argument of iuſt iudging,</hi> How oft would I haue gathered you together and ye would not? <hi>if they could doe no otherwiſe?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Wee are bidden to turne, to ſhew that the Lord will not turne vs without our being willing, and by thus calling vpon vs, he worketh a willingneſſe, in ſuch as bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected: and if any notwithſtanding are ſtill hardened, and finally damned, the cauſe is not in God, who is tyed to no man, but in the corruption of their owne will, brought in by mans owne default, when at the firſt it was not ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the twelfth particular point?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>The twelfth point is, that mariage is free for all men, and that none ought to be debarred from it: but if any can containe, they are to bee exhorted to vſe this gift, that they may be more free to ſerue God, not being intangled with ſo much worldly buſineſſe, as they which haue wife
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3008:11"/>and children. For <hi>mariage is honorable amongst all men:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 13.4. 1 Tim 4 3.</note> and it is <hi>a doctrine of Deuils forbidding to marry;</hi> yea the Apoſtles themſelues were maried men, and I might haue vſed the ſame libertie alſo, neither doth the Lord approue it to bee good for any ſort of men, <hi>not to marry,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 19.12.</note> but for ſuch onely as <hi>can containe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>If mariage bringeth worldly incombrances, and the Miniſters of the Goſpell had need to enioy all freedome, that they may the better attend vpon their office, it ſeemeth, that the vnmaried are rather to bee preferred, if a ſufficient number of ſuch may be had: and if any bee therefore willing to liue alwaies ſingle, that they may be the more fit for this ſeruice, it is no for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding of mariaege to receiue onely ſuch to holy Orders. Againe, though mariage be lawfull, and a mans companying with his wife be no ſinne, yet it diſableth him for a time to communicate in ſuch things, as wherein holy perſons onely haue libertie, as to eate of the Shew-bread.</hi> Abiathar <hi>telleth</hi> Dauid,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 21.4.</note> 
                  <hi>that if they</hi> had not lately companied with women <hi>they might cate of it, and the Prieſts vnder the Law, when their courſe came to ſerue in the Temple, liued apart from their wiues, as appeareth by the example of</hi> Zachary.<note place="margin">Luk. 1.23.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>If any ſufficient and fit for life and learning, hauing the gift of continencie liue ſingle, it is not to bee doubted, but that they are to be preferred: but becauſe this gift is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rare, and for preferment men will take vpon them that, which they haue no abilitie vnto, to admit onely ſuch into holy Orders, is in effect to forbid mariage to ſome, and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, as of the Deuill, as hath been already ſhewed. Yea it is a maruell, that they which pretend the Apoſtolicall title ſo much, ſhould bee ſo plainely againſt the Apoſtle, who ſaith; <hi>Let a Biſhop be the Husband of one Wife.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.</note> Neither are they that inforce themſelues to a ſingle life, but want the gift, the more free, but rather much more troubled, ſeeing luſt is an hundreth times more incombring, then any domeſticall troubles of the maried. And laſtly, if it bee a good reaſon againſt the mariage of Prieſts, that companying with wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men makes them vnfit to partake of the Holy Bread for a time, it is good alſo againſt the mariage of any Chriſtian
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3008:12"/>man, who is now alſo to partake of this bread, as well as the Prieſt. No more therefore can be hence concluded, but that all ſhould abſtaine from companying with their wiues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the time of communicating, as againſt the time of faſting &amp; Prayer. For ſo I haue elſewhere directed. <hi>Defraud not one another,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 7 5.</note> 
                  <hi>except it be by conſent for a time, that ye may giue your ſelues to faſting and Prayer, and come together againe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the thirteenth particular point?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>The thirteenth point is, that the holy Scriptures, that is, the canonicall bookes of the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are alone ſufficient for ſaluation, neither are any other either Apochryphall Writings, or vnwritten Traditions of like authoritie, but onely ſo far forth to be receiued, as they agree with the contents of theſe Bookes. For it is plainely expreſſed, that though Ieſus did and ſpake many things more, then are written, <hi>yet theſe things are written, that wee might beleeue, and beleeuing haue eternall life.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 20.31. Gal. 1 8.</note> And <hi>if we, or an Angell from Heauen, bring any other Goſpell, let him bee accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> We that are the Apoſtles of Chriſt haue euer ſubmitted our doctrine to bee examined by the written Word, and therefore,<note place="margin">Act. 17.11.</note> if any thing be pretended to haue been taught by vs by word of mouth, or by any that haue followed vs, not conſonant to the written Word, it is without doubt to bee reiected.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is no where written, that the Lords day is to bee kept holy in ſtead of the old Sabbath, nor that infants are to bee baptized, nor that the Lords Supper is to bee receiued in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or at the Church, or by women as well as by men, and yet theſe things are neceſſarie.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe are agreeable to the written Word, and therefore good reaſon, that they ſhould bee obſerued: but this maketh nothing for vnwritten traditions contrary to the Word of God, or for the authoritie of any, that are without ground here.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Scriptures are obſcure, and therefore alledged euen by the vileſt Heretikes, ſo that if they onely be receiued, it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that there will be nothing to patronize the truth, more then errour. It is not therefore neceſſarie to take them with the ſenſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3008:12"/>receiued by the Church, that wee may hold aright, and be ſaued?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Many places of Scripture are plaine, and eaſie to be vnderſtood; namely, ſo many, as doe ſet forth the Articles of our faith, Gods holy will and commandements, and the doctrine of Prayer, and worſhipping God, which is all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to be knowne vnto ſaluation; ſo that herein a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian of ordinarie vnderſtanding, needeth not to depend vpon the ſenſe of others, but immediately vpon the Word of God. In places more obſcure, the beſt Doctors of the Church haue alwayes differed; and therefore euen herein Chriſtian people are not tyed to the ſenſe of any, but to that, which is moſt agreeable to the truth, plainely ſet forth in ſome other place.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>If all haue iudgement in the ſenſe of Gods Word, then it ſeemeth that none are to bee debarred from reading the Scriptures, for feare of falling into errour by ſo doing: whereas it is plaine, that ignorant perſons are peruerted ſometimes by the ſcriptures themſelues.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>For,</hi> there are many places hard to be vnderſtood, which the ignorant and vnſtable peruert to their owne damnation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Nothing can be more againſt the minde of Chriſt, then to debarre the people from reading, and hearing the Scriptures read in a knowne tongue. For hee hath bidden, <hi>Search the Scriptures, for therein yee looke to finde eternall life.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh 5.39.</note> The danger that ſome fall into hereby is otherwiſe to bee prouided againſt: <hi>viz.</hi> by diligent preaching, and opening the ſenſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But is not the Church all in all to Chriſtian peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Haue they not the Scriptures from the Church? and do they not by the Church come to know, that they are the Word of God? and therefore howſoeuer the Church ſhall order the reading and ſetting forth of the Scriptures, is it not to be held to be done very well?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>It is not to bee denied, but that as the Woman of Samaria brought the people there to the knowledge of Chriſt, ſo we are brought by the Church, at the firſt, to know the Scriptures to be the Word of God: but as the ſame peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſaid vnto her, after that Chriſt had taught them:<note place="margin">Ioh 4.42.</note> now <hi>we
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3008:13"/>beleeue, not becauſe of thy words, but becauſe we haue heard him our ſelues:</hi> So Chriſtian people receiuing the Word into their hearts, doe not beleeue any more becauſe of the Church, but becauſe the Word it ſelfe working vpon their conſciences perſwadeth them, that it is the Word of God. And as it gaue the being at the firſt vnto the Church, ſo the Church is to bee ordered thereby, as by the ſuperiour, and not to order it, as an inferiour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the fourteenth particular point?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>The fourteenth point is, that Chriſt onely is the ſupreme head and foundation of his Church, neither hath any one man, nor ought to haue ſuperioritie ouer all others in ſpirituall matters, in all Countries and Nations, being as it were a common Rocke, whereupon all may ſtay them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, nothing doubting, but that cleaning to him, they cleaue to Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3 9.</note> and are free from errour. For, <hi>none can lay any other foundation, ſauing that which is laid, Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> If vpon any other the Church be founded, it is not vpon one, but vpon all the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> alike,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.20 Gal. 2.9.</note> and <hi>the Prophets</hi> too: if vpon any as more principall they are three, <hi>Iames, Cephas,</hi> and <hi>Iohn, who ſeemed to be Pillars.</hi> If a power ſpiritually to rule by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening, and ſhutting, binding, and looſing, be committed to any ouer all others, neither is that committed to one <hi>Peter,</hi> but to all the Apoſtles:<note place="margin">Ioh. 20 23.</note> For, <hi>whoſe ſins ye remit,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>they are remitted, and whoſe ſinnes yee retaine, they are retained:</hi> and if any one hath rule ouer the world, as chiefe, it is not <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 2 7.</note> but <hi>Paul:</hi> For, <hi>to</hi> Peter <hi>was committed the miniſterie of the circumciſion</hi> onely, which was but of one Nation; to <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>miniſter of the vncircumciſion,</hi> which was of all the reſt of the world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But of</hi> Peter <hi>the Lord ſaith ſingularly:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 16.16.</note> Thou art <hi>Peter,</hi> and vpon this Rocke will I build my Church, and to thee I giue the Keyes of the Kingdome of Heauen. <hi>And,</hi> follow me, and I will make thee a fiſher of men. <hi>And againe,</hi> Peter loueſt thou me?<note place="margin">Ioh. 23.</note> Feed my ſheepe. <hi>By all which it ſhould ſeemt, that howſoeuer others had power of binding and looſing too, yet he was preferred, as chiefe, and aboue all the reſt, after whom ſuch another ſhould ſucceed, and ſo another from age to age to the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3008:13"/>worlds end. And this conſtruction ſeemeth to bee verified by the vninterrupted ſucceſſion of thoſe Biſhops, who challenge to be his ſucceſſors, beyond all other Biſhops of any other place, ſeeing there is no ſuch ſucreſſion elſe where to be found?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>If <hi>Peter</hi> had beene appointed ouer all, I had beene much to blame <hi>to withſtand him to his face at Antioch,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 2.14.</note> and to goe on in mine office without ſeeking allowance and aduice from him. I doe not therefore acknowledge any chiefly intimated in <hi>Peter</hi> aboue the other Apoſtles, but that hee ſhould be a moſt notable inſtrument of glorifying God, and propagating the Goſpell, wherein hee ſhould exceed the reſt, being fuller of the power of the Holy Ghoſt, as he was fuller of zeale towards Chriſt. And that laſt committing of the ſheepe and lambs to his feeding ſingularly, was no more then was needfull after his groſſe fall by denying his Lord and Maſter, through which hee might for euer haue beene diſcouraged, had not his commiſſion beene againe renued. It pleaſed our good God for his owne glory to deale alike with him, and with me, both grieuous ſinners and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, that where ſinne had moſt abounded, zeale and grace might moſt abound; and whereas wee were moſt darkned, through ſcandall that might hence ariſe, making vs vnfit to be lights of the world, to make vs ſhine by miracles aboue all others, that thus no ſcandall to hinder the Goſpell might any more appeare. And as for the ſucceſſion ſo much glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in, it is no true ſucceſſion of Apoſtolicall men, but of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticall Princes, maintained by the ſword, and not by the word, euen as the ſucceſſors of <hi>Mahomet</hi> haue done. Of Apoſtlolike men there hath beene a more true ſucceſſion at Conſtantinople, Alexandria, and Antioch.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But if there be no ſupreame power vpon earth, how ſhall vnity be maintained in the Church, ſeeing diners men will be of diners minds? and in caſe of difference about matter of faith, who ſhall be Iudge to end it? if no one man, how ſhall it come to an end? or hath the Lord left his Church in ſuch a miſerable caſe, as that ſhe muſt needs broile in contentions without end?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>There was no ſupreame in the Primitiue Church, and yet they are ſaid to <hi>haue beens all together with one mind;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 2.46.</note>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:3008:14"/>the Spirit which is the Author of vnity, ſhall keepe the true Church in vnity, though there be no viſible head ouer all. And as for differences that ariſe, wee haue an exemplary di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to meet in Councell:<note place="margin">Acts 15.</note> Where being free liberty for any learned member to ſpeake, it is not to bee doubted, but that the aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt being inuocated, after reaſonable debating of things controuerted, all ſhall bee ſwayed to hearken vnto and determine with one eminent man, as they did with <hi>Iames.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ 22.</note> If not, but as in the time of Arrianiſme more are for error then for the truth, it muſt be borne as a croſſe, till the Lord will be entreated to giue the truth the victory againe, as he did then after certaine yeres. And thus I haue related all the chiefe points of the faith maintained by the Proteſtant Church, ſo plaily founded vpon the word of God, as that if in any of them there be er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, we may cry out with the Prophet,<note place="margin">Ier. 20.7.</note> and ſay, <hi>If we be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued (O God) thou haſt deceiued vs.</hi> There be many points more, but becauſe they will better come vnder thoſe that concerne practice, I will refer them thither.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are the points concerning practice?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, as we hold that God onely is to be beleeued in, ſo we make all our prayers to him onely, vtterly refuſing to pray to Angels or Saints departed, how gracious ſoeuer they may ſeeme to be with the Lord: And herein wee haue warrant from the word of God, who ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Call vpon mee in the time of trouble, and I will heare and deliuer thee.</hi> Thus all the faith full, whoſe practice is recorded in holy Scriptures, haue alwayes done, neither hath any euer called vpon any other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Did not</hi> Iaacob <hi>pray to the Angell that was with him in all his peregrination,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 48.16.</note> 
                  <hi>that he would bleſſe the two ſons of</hi> Ioſeph, Ephraim <hi>and</hi> Manaſſeh, <hi>when he ſaid,</hi> God before whom my fathers did walke, the God, which fed me all my life long vnto this day, the Angell, which redeemed mee from all euill, bleſſe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ads, &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>The Angell named here, is none other but the Lord Ieſus: for where doe we reade of any other Redeemer? If he had meant an Angell, as the word is commonly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3008:14"/>he would haue ſaid Angels, and not an Angell, for at all times of danger mention is made of the Angels appearing to him, as both in his iourney towards Padan Aram,<note place="margin">Gen. 28.10. Gen. 32.1.</note> and in his returne from thence. Onely hee, to whom his deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from <hi>Eſau</hi> is to be imputed, wreſtled with him alone, of whom the Text ſpeaketh ſo plainly, as that it is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine he was the Lord. If <hi>Iaacob</hi> ſhould haue prayed to an Angell, how farre an Angell would haue beene from accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of it, appeareth in the example of <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> who were both forbidden to worſhip an Angell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the ſecond point in practice?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe God is a Spirit, which cannot be expreſſed by any ſimilitude, wee abhorre the vſe of any image or ſimilitude in diuine worſhip: yea we refraine alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether from ſetting forth the diuine Maieſty by any image. For, both <hi>Moſes</hi> chargeth the people,<note place="margin">Deur. 4.15.</note> that they <hi>make no image, becauſe they ſaw none in the day that the Lord ſpake to them;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 40.</note> and the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeaketh of it as a thing impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to repreſent God, who is infinite, by a finite reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance; and <hi>Hahakkuk</hi> plainly calleth images teachers of lyes.<note place="margin">Hab. 2.18.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But God hath ſometime aſſumed a ſhape vnto himſelfe, as to</hi> Daniel <hi>he appeared like an old man, at Chriſts bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme the Holy Ghoſt appeared in the likeneſſe of a Doue. Why may he not then be thus pictured and ſet forth?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>The precepts of God, and not his actions, ought to be a direction to vs; ſo that if he hath forbidden to make an image of God, it will bee no good plea to alledge how hee hath ſometime appeared, if we preſume thus to picture him. Beſides, all images made by man are dead things, whereas the reſemblances which God hath at any time appeared by haue had life and motion. And ſuch a picture of God is any huing man, rather then a dead and dumb image. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, theſe reſemblances were not exhibited to bee worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, but onely to expreſſe in viſion, what the Lord would haue his people to vnderſtand.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>An image putteth a man in mind of God, who is apt otherwiſe to be caried away with by-thoughts.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:3008:15"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Shall man take vpon him to bee wiſer then God; when hee hath commanded to make no image, but to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him in ſpirit, what it is in effect but to inſtruct him? What wilt thou, that no image be made, but onely that the minde be fixed vpon thee in Prayer: thou doeſt not ſo adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly herein, becauſe mens minds are ready to bee drawne away if they haue nothing to behold. It were much better therefore for them to haue ſome image to keepe the minde from wandring, and to ſtirre vp deuotion. Oh intolerable ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancie, that man ſhould dare thus to correct the precepts of his Maker.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth the command of God touch Images, or rather Heathen Idols, which are repreſentations of falſe gods, which hee forbiddeth to haue in the firſt command: and then to make ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of them in the ſecond?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Indeed, ſome are much deluded hereby, thinking that their image-making is throughly iuſtified thus. But ſilly men that they are, they doe little attend the vehement inuectiues of the Prophets, againſt ſuch as attempted by image, to repreſent the True God, both becauſe it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and becauſe it is the way to let in much corruption in the worſhip of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>It ſeemeth, that the Lord was delighted in images about his Tabernacle, and Temple; for hee appointed Cherubins to be made in moſt glorious maner, which had faces like yong men: ſo that the garniſhing of Churches with images now is not a thing ſo vnwarrantable, and without preſident, as you would make it to be.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Thoſe images were onely for ornament, and haply for ſome ſignification, but for adoration there is not the leaſt ſyllable, that tendeth to ſhew that they were: neither did they ſerue to reſemble God, but in ſome ſort in what ſtate and maieſtie the Lord ſitteth in Heauen, attended by ſuch glorious creatures. It cannot be gathered hence, that Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches may now bee garniſhed in like manner, becauſe then they were much taught by outward things, as children in their nonage, but now being of full age, we are no more <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der beggarly and impotent rudiments.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 4.9.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:3008:15"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the third point in practice?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Thirdly, becauſe the Lord Ieſus hath bidden vs aske any thing in his Name; wee pray alwayes in the name of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt onely to the Father, flying as ſacrilege, prayers vnto Saints departed. For it is the proper honour of Chriſt to ſeek vnto God by his mediation.<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.2.</note> 
                  <hi>If any man ſinne, wee haue an aduocate with the Father, Ieſus Chriſt the righteous.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to vſe the mediation of others, it is to rob Chriſt of his honour. Euen as if the Prince ſhould bid vs all, that haue ſuits to the King, to come to him, and he will prefer them for vs: if notwithſtanding we leauing the Prince, ſhould flocke about ſome Courtiers to intercede for vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the fourth point in practice?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Fourthly, wee make all our prayers in a knowne tongue: for, <hi>I will pray with the ſpirit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.15.</note> 
                  <hi>and I will pray with my vnderſtanding alſo.</hi> It is a confuſion, and no edification to vſe publike ſeruice in a ſtrange tongue, euen as when a trumpet maketh an imperfect ſound.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the fifth point in practice?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Fiftly, becauſe the Lord hath forbidden vaine repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions,<note place="margin">Math. 6.</note> as heatheniſh: we doe not place deuotion in ſaying ouer a multitude of prayers, but in feruent and hearty pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; one, or a few prayers at a time, ſo as that our affections may be quickened, and not dulled hereby.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the ſixth point in practice?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Sixtly, wee content our ſelues to confeſſe our ſinnes only to God, and hold it not neceſſary to confeſſe all things vnto the Prieſt, but onely for neceſſary reliefe of conſcience, being troubled in regard of ſome particulars. And general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wee deny not, but acknowledge to one another, that wee are ſinners, and this is all that God hath commanded.<note place="margin">Iam. 5.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe your ſinnes one vnto another, and pray one for another.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the ſeuenth point in practice?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Seuenthly, when we haue humbled our ſelues for our ſinnes, wee doe not take vpon vs to ſatisfie for them by puniſhing our bodies with whipping, or putting on Haire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, but onely by abſtinence and contrition of heart, wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching more carefully ouer our wayes, that wee ſinne no
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3008:16"/>more. For Chriſt hath ſatisfied fully for vs, by bearing in his bodie the ſmart due for our ſins, and no more reuenge is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to be taken by vs vpon our ſelues: but that whereby our bodies may be beaten downe,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.</note> and the better kept from ſinning for the time to come, ſuch as is hearty ſorrow, for ſo the Lord hath commanded;<note place="margin">Ioel 2.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Rent your hearts and not your garments:</hi> and faſting is often called for, but doing violence to the body, by ſtriking till the blood commeth out, is rather to imitate <hi>Baals</hi> prieſts,<note place="margin">1 King. 18.</note> that lanched and cut their bodies in their ſuperſtitious deuotion, then to follow any approued patterne of the truely godly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the wearing of ſackcloth and aſhes is commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by many approued examples, ſo that if you refuſe this penance, it ſeemeth, that you are iuſtly to blame.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Wee muſt not confound, but diſtinguiſh betwixt times. Vnder the Law indeed theſe things were required, and the waſhing of the body, and the bringing of a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, for expiation of ſinne; becauſe the Lord not content with inward contrition, would haue it outwardly expreſſed alſo; ſuch was the auſteritie of the Law: but vnder the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, theſe are remitted: for when the Publicans and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple asked <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 3.9.</note> exhorting to workes of repentance, what they ſhould doe, he omitteth all theſe things, and ſpeaketh onely of ceaſing from ſinne, and doing good; neither is gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with ſackcloth, &amp;c. any where elſe mentioned in the New Teſtament, ſuch is the lenitie of the Goſpel. Hereupon it is ſaid, that the burthen of the Law was heauy, and ſuch <hi>at neither we nor our fathers were able to heare:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 15.10. Math. 11.28.</note> but of the yoake of the Goſpell, the Lord ſaith: <hi>My yoake is eaſie, and my bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den light.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But are not ſome ſinnes veniall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for which Chriſt did not, neither needed to ſuffer? and ought not wee then by theſe workes of penance to ſatisfie for them?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>It is an imaginaly diſtinction, no where founded in the Word of God:<note place="margin">Iam. 2.10. Math. 5.19.</note> for here all ſinne is condemned as mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall. <hi>He that obſerueth all the Law, and yet faileth in one point, it guilty of all. He that breaketh the leaſt of Gods commandements, and teacheth others to doe ſo, ſhal be counted the leaſt in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3008:16"/>of Heauen.</hi> And what leſſer ſin can there be then an idle word,<note place="margin">Math. 12.36. Mark. 7.21.</note> and yet hereof <hi>account ſhall bee giuen at the day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> And what leſſer then euill thoughts, and yet theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file a man, and ſo debatre him from heauen, foraſmuch as <hi>no vncleane thing ſhall enter therein.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the eighth point of practice?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apoc. 22.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Eighthly, we hold that we may as acceptably wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God in one place, as in another; namely, in our priuate worſhip one alone, neither haue wee need to goe on pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to any remote place, where the bones of any Saint, or Reliques are kept, or Church or Chappell in any reſpect ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be more holy, as though wee ſhould the rather ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Gods indulgence, in reſpect of our ſinnes, by thus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. For when <hi>thou wilt pray,</hi> ſaith the Lord,<note place="margin">Math. 6.6.</note> 
                  <hi>enter into thy cloſet.</hi> And for publique aſſembling to the worſhip of God, any conſecrate place is as good as Ieruſalem, or the Mount, where <hi>Iacob</hi> was wont to worſhip. For all ſuch dignitie of one place aboue another, is plainly by Chriſt himſelfe abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated, ſaying: <hi>The houre commeth, when neither at Ieruſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 4.20.</note> 
                  <hi>nor in this Mountaine men ſhall worſhip the Father.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the ninth point of practice?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Ninthly, if any bee ſicke, wee pray for them, but anoint them not,<note place="margin">Iam. 5.</note> becauſe although direction bee giuen thus to doe, yet conſideration muſt be had of the times, anointing was then accompanied with healing, through a ſingular ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue vpon the Presbyterie, for the more confirmation of the Goſpel, in the firſt beginnings thereof, but this hath ceaſed long agoe, and therefore if it were now vſed, it would bee a naked ceremonie, without benefit to the diſeaſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the tenth point of practice?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Tenthly, we doe not vſe croſſing or Holy Water, or any the like Ceremonies to bleſſe vs therewith: becauſe we doe not finde, that they were inſtituted by God, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented by men giuen to ſuperſtition, and therefore can haue no further vertue, then ſuch are able to giue vnto them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But by experience it hath beene diuers times confirmed, that there is vertue in theſe things: for the diuell hath beene often hereby chaced away.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:3008:17"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>If any ſuch effect hath followed vpon the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying of them, it hath beene through colluſion of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, giuing way for a further aduantage: namely, that ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious people might be the more confirmed, in their confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in ſuch impotent ceremonies, and be drawne away from God, who onely is able to curbe Satan; that thus they might lye the more open vnto him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the eleuenth point of practice?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Eleuenthly, we do not vſe any deceit, by keeping any thing written in the canonicall Scriptures, from the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the people, or by inuenting ſtories of things neuer done, to ſtirre vp deuotion in them. For whatſoeuer the pretence may be in thus doing, wee are ſure that God hath pronounced them accurſed,<note place="margin">Deut. 4.</note> that take ought from his lawes, or adde any thing thereunto.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the twelfth point of practice?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>In the twelfth place, we doe not commend wilfull pouertie, as a point of deuotion, that is, for a man to giue away all that he hath to the poore, ſo that himſelfe is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to begge for reliefe. For we are not to giue ſo, as that <hi>we may be grieued, and others eaſed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.13. 1 Cor. 16.1.</note> but <hi>euery man as God hath bleſſed him,</hi> and as he can ſpare.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt was poore, and ſo were the Apoſtles, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him that asked, what he was yet to doe, it is preſcribed, if</hi> thou wilt be perfect,<note place="margin">Math. 19 21.</note> goe ſell all that which thou haſt, and giue it to the poore: <hi>and according to this direction, they</hi> that had poſſeſſions,<note place="margin">Act. 4.</note> ſold them, and brought the price, and laid it at the Apoſtles feet. <hi>And laſtly, the poore are pronounced bleſſed, and woe is to the rich, and full.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Chriſt was borne poore, the Diſciples forſooke all to attend vpon their Apoſtolicall Office, which neceſſarily required<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, and to this Office was that Yong man called, who was bidden to ſell and giue to the poore; ſo that what is ſaid to him bindeth not but in the like caſe: <hi>viz.</hi> when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man is called, the neceſſitie of the Church requiring it, in an Apoſtolike manner, to trauell through diuers countreys to ſet forth the Goſpell. Touching that example of ſelling and laying downe the price at the Apoſtles feet, it was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3008:17"/>and only of ſuch as ioyned themſelues with the Apoſtles, for the publike ſeruice of the Church, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſoone ceaſed, as appeareth, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.13. Laſtly, the poore ſimply are not pronounced bleſſed, nor the rich woful: for he ſaith onely, <hi>Bleſſed are ye poore:</hi> namely,<note place="margin">Luke 6.20.</note> which haue left all to follow, and ſerue me in this Office: and, <hi>Wee to you that are rich,</hi> that is, preferre your riches ſo, as that like the Yong man, ye refuſe to leaue them, to follow me, though hereunto inuited.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the thirteenth point of practice?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>In the thirteenth place, we doe not vow perpetuall Virginitie, as ſuppoſing it a point of more perfection; nor to liue in Cels, Wilderneſſes, or Monaſteries, there to ſpend our time ſeparate from the world, in the nabit, and according to the rules preſcribed by the inſtituters of ſuch Orders, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying to be of their Order. For wee ought not to vow any thing, but what we can performe, but this wee cannot, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not giuen to all. And for Monaſticall liuing, it is plainely repugnant to this.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Let euery man continue in that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, wherein God hath called him.</hi> And to be named after any man, I haue by the Spirit of God condemned as carnall, in the perſons of thoſe at <hi>Corinth,</hi> that held <hi>ſome of</hi> Paul,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>ſome of</hi> Cephas, &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the fourteenth point of practice?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>In the fourteenth place, we keep Holy-dayes in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of Chriſt, the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and of the holy Apoſtles, as being ſet forth in the Word of God, for moſt notable and holy inſtruments of our beſt good: but other dayes dedicated to others we obſerue not: partly, leſt the people ſhould be ouermuch burdened with dayes; and partly, becauſe we are vncertaine of the worth of ſuch men, or the truth of ſuch things, as in remembrance whereof theſe obſeruations were taken vp.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the fifteenth point of practice?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>In the fifteenth place, wee keepe faſts of Lent, and Holy-dayes-eues, &amp;c. according to the ancient cuſtome of the Church of God, but wee reckon not this to be any part of Gods ſeruice, but a meanes, the better to enable vs againſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3008:18"/>the fleſh, and to the ſpirituall ſernice. Neither doe wee thinke the conſcience defiled at ſuch times by cating fleſh: for <hi>nothing that entreth into a man defileth him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 7.20.</note> but onely that they which doe thus, are worthily fined, for neglecting wholeſome conſtituted Orders When there is any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar occaſion to faſt, wee abſtaine from all food, from mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning till night.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the ſixteenth point of practice?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>In the ſixteenth place, we all both Clergie and Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie are ſubiect to our King as Supreme; and to his Officers, whom we are bound to obey vnder him: and if he doth ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannize ouer vs, if hee be an Hereticke, or ſetter vp of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, we reſiſt not by force, neither by treachery ſeeke to take his life away; but we exhort him, and pray for him, and ſo leaue him to the Lord, who onely is aboue him, and can juſtly chaſtiſe him. For thus <hi>Dauid</hi> behaued himſelfe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Saul,</hi> and I haue plainely ſet it downe as a charge to all;<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1. 1 Tim. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Let euery ſoule be ſubiect to the higher powers:</hi> and <hi>let pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers be made for all, eſpecially for Kings, and Gouernours, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the ſeuenteenth point of practice?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>In the ſeuenteenth place, wee proceed in that ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple manner in our baptizing, that our Sauiour Chriſt hath preſcribed, vſing neither Milke, nor Honey, nor Spittle, nor Salt, nor exorciſing, but onely Water, in the name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Sonne, and the Holy Ghoſt, and certaine prayers, and ſitting admonitions before and after. For all other things were brought in ſince, and ſo are humane and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But ye vſe a ſpeciall veſtiment, and the ſigne of the Croſſe in your baptizing?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Wee doe ſo indeed, but not as any neceſſary appur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances of Baptiſme; but the Surplice is put on for order as a diſtinguiſhing garment; and the Croſſe is made after bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſine ended, without opinion of any vertue in it, onely to figure out what a baſe profeſſion in the opinion of the world we betake our ſelues vnto, we being yet no whit aſhamed of the ignominie of Chriſts Croſſe, but reioycing to beare eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man the Croſſe, which he ſhall meet withall for his ſake.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:3008:18"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the eighteenth point of practice?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>In the eighteenth place, we receiue the Sacrament of the Lords Supper with all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>erence vpon nor knees, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this ended, we do not keep the Holy bread remaining to be caried about in Proceſſion, as hauing vertue to any other vſe, but onely to ſeed the ſoules of ſuch as are preſent. If any be ſicke, which deſire it, other bread and Wine are taken; and being by the Miniſter conſecrated, as in publike it is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the ſicke, and to ſome others with him. Moreouer, we vſe common Bread and Wine, and not little Cakes of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leauened bread to be giuen whole, being firſt lifted vp in the ſight of the people, that they may worſhip them. For this vſe onely of this bleſſed Sacrament haue we from our Lord Chriſt, and to bring in any other vſe, is to preſume to bee wiſer then he, and ſo to become ſtarke fooles. And thus I haue faithfully related the practice of the Reformed or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But why is this called the Reformed Church? hath Chriſt any more Churches but one?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>No: the Church of Chriſt is but one, whereſoeuer diſperſed in all the world: but this Church partly through the ambition and couetouſneſſe of the Popes of Rome, and of the reſt of the chiefe of the Clergie, and partly through blind deuotion, became very corrupt, both in doctrine, and manner of ſeruing God, wherein hauing lyon many yeares to the griefe of the truely zealous and wiſe, who did what they could or durſt to rectifie things againe, but without ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, at length (though very loth ſo to doe) many without feare of bodily danger ſeparated themſelues from all ſociety and communion with thoſe, that ſtill adliered to theſe cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, teaching and holding as hath be one before deela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; who notwithſtanding the hot brunts of perſecution, which they met withall, increaſed dayly; whole Countreys and Kingdomes, being in a ſhort time by Gods prouidence ioyned vnto them. And becauſe of this reformation, about which they made then proteſtation, that ſimply for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience towards God, and his Truth, and onely according to his written Word they thus proceeded, they were called
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3008:19"/>the Reformed or Proteſtant Church: others willfully cleauing to their corruptions ſtill, and to the Pope and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Clergy, the chiefe maintainers hereof, were called the Church of Rome, or the Popiſh Church, or as they needes will haue it, Roman Catholikes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then it ſeemeth, that the Church anciently one, is now become two, the one oppoſite to the other. Or, are they both one Church ſtill, but diuided for their contrary opinions, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in many things?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>As the Church of Chriſt hath beene, ſo it ſtill is, and euer ſhall bee one, and not two; for it is Chriſt; Spouſe, which is onely one. I doe not therefore acknowledge, but aduiſedly deny the Church of Rome to be a true Church of Chriſt:<note place="margin">Reu. 3.1.</note> As the Church of <hi>Sardis</hi> had <hi>a name to be aline, but was dead,</hi> ſo it may hold this name ſtill, but is indeed a very carkaſſe without a ſoule, by reaſon of the groſſe errours therein maintained and practiſed: for truth is the life of the Church. The reformed Church then is the onely true Church, neither may we returne againe to them vpon paine of damnation: but they muſt and ſhall come to vs at the laſt; for truth is ſtronger then all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the maine truth is ſtill maintained in the Church of Rome:</hi> viz. <hi>That Ieſus is the Sonne of God: and haſt not thou thy ſelfe taught,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor 3.</note> 
                  <hi>that who ſo buildeth vpon the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation Chriſt Ieſus, though but hay or ſtubble, which ſhall hurne, yet himſelfe ſhall eſcape as it were through the fire? What is this, but that ſo Chriſt bee cleaued vnto, no erroneous opinions or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in the ſeruice of God ſhall damne the ſoule.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>The Church of Rome teacheth indeed generally this truth touching Chriſt Ieſus, but in the particular ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of what they hold hereabout, they doe plainly raze this foundation, and ſo their building is not vpon the foundation Chriſt deſcribed in the New Teſtament, but imagined in their owne braines. Againe, although the foundation were rightly held, yet they are builders onely that ſhall be ſaued, not deſtroyers or demoliſhers, as they of the Church of Rome are.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherein doe they raze the foundation Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:3008:19"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>In that they doe not rely vpon Chriſt only for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation and grace. For this is the property of a foundation, to beare vp all the building alone, if it be the only foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as I haue taught, that Chriſt is. If then the building reſt partly vpon ſome other foundation, this is in effect razed, becauſe though this be ſound, yet the other vpon which it partly ſtandeth being deceitfull and vnſound, when that ſhall faile, the whole building cannot but come downe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>It ſeemeth then, that Chriſt is the foundation to them onely that reſt vpon him alone; and that they which together with him rely vpon any thing elſe, are in effect gone from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and ſo ſhall haue no more benefit of it, then they that hold not Chriſt at all. Can you proue the Roman Catholikes to be ſuch?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>There is nothing more plaine to them that will vnderſtand. For firſt, when Chriſt only is relyed vpon, and ſo made the onely ſoundation, his paſſions alone are held to be fully ſatisfactory for all puniſhments due to vs for all our ſins both temporall and eternall. Secondly, all merit where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we become worthy of ſaluation is held to be in him one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Thirdly, His mediation onely to God the Father, is reſted vpon to obtaine any benefit or helpe in the time of need. Fourthly, The beginning, progreſſe and perfection of all grace is imputed to him onely through the working of his Spirit, and nothing to a mans ſelfe. But the contrary to all theſe are maintained in the Church of Rome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Declare this more particularly, and firſt, that they rely not vpon his paſſions onely as fully ſatisfactory.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>They ſay that he hath ſatisfied for all eternall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in hell, but not for temporall: for theſe are left to vs to be ſatisfied for, partly here by acts of penance, and partly hereafter in purgatory. And that there are certaine leſſer ſinnes called veniall, for which we our ſelues muſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie. Flatly contrary to Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> who ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Ioh 1.6.</note> 
                  <hi>the blood of Ieſus Chriſt cleanſeth vs from all ſin.</hi> And I haue taught <hi>that Chriſt hath redeemed vs from the curſe of the Law being made a curſe for vs:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 3.13.</note> Now this curſe did as well extend to temporall as eternall puniſhments, witneſſe <hi>Moſes</hi> his dilating vpon it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. and <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26. throughout which Chapters
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3008:20"/>he ſheweth that the curſe comming by ſinne is temporall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>If Chriſt had ſatisfied herein for vs, were it not iniuſtice in God to put his to ſo much ſmart againe daily, by ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, loſſes, ignominies, and perſecutions in the world?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>It were iniuſtice indeed, if our ſins being forgiuen and clenſed away in Chriſts blood, hee ſhould ſtill require vs to be temporally paniſhed.<note place="margin">Luke 23.16.</note> This were iuſt <hi>Pilates</hi> iuſtice. <hi>I finde no fault in this man, I will therefore ſcourge him, and let him goe.</hi> God forbid, that wee ſhould once thinke the moſt righteous Lord to be ſuch in his proceedings. It is to bee vnderſtood therefore, that the ſmart impoſed vpon vs here is onely either for our triall, or for our correction in loue, as parents are wont to deale with their children.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What doe they hold touching merit?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>That Chriſts death and paſſion alone, are not the meritorious cauſe of our ſaluation, but the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and the holy Apoſtles, and other Saints which haue ſuffered death for the Goſpell, haue alſo merited for vs; and that there is merit in the ſacrifice of the Maſſe, extended to all both quicke and dead; and in the workes of the regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate through which they become worthy of heauen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Saints are ſo neere vnto Chriſt, as that it ſeemeth to be all one to aſcribe merit vnto their paſſions, and to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> if they were diuerſe from him, it were to lay another foundation indeed. Haſt not thou written to the ſame effect ſaying,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 1.24.</note> I ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill thereſt of the afflictions of Chriſt in my fleſh for his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy which is his Church? <hi>And touching the Maſſe, and good workes of the regenerate, whatſoeuer vertue is aſcribed hereunto, it tendeth the more to the magniſying of Chriſts merit, which is able to giue vertue to other things to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rit alſo.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe are plauſible reaſons indeed to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ceiue the ſimple, but he which hath any vnderſtanding can conſider, that by the like reaſon the ſunne, moone and ſtarres, might ſafety be aſſociated vnto God in diuine worſhip, for they are neere vnto him alſo. And for that ſaying of mine, if any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part of my writing, or of the whole Bible did ſound to the ſeconding of ſuch an acception, it might well bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſo: but conſidering, that I haue plainly profeſſed elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3008:20"/>that Paul <hi>is nothing, and</hi> Apoſlo <hi>nothing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. Phil. 3.9.</note> and that Chriſts righteouſneſſe is that onely wherein I <hi>deſire to bee found.</hi> Mee thinkes what I haue ſaid to the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> ſhould not be wreſted ſo, but bee ſimply taken of my ſufferings, in going about to doe good vnto the Church, which I call Chriſts ſufferings, becauſe vndergone for him, who taught me ſometime,<note place="margin">Act. 9.</note> that the perſecuting of his members was the perſecuting of himſelfe. Laſtly, where there is any ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the vertue of Chriſts paſſion to make other things meritorious certaine, it is good to acknowledge and extoll it, but out of this caſe, as it is in the matter of the Maſſe, and of good workes, it is a plaine derogating from Chriſts merit the onely ſure foundation, and a razing of it. That there is no merit in theſe things hath beene ſufficiently ſhewed heretofore.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But did not the bleſſed Virgin</hi> Mary <hi>merit any thing for vs by thoſ paſſions, which ſhe had together with Chriſt in her ſoule, when he hung vpon the Croſſe?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>I am glad that you put me in mind againe to ſpeak of this, that the abhomination of the Romiſh religion might the more appeare. For indeed they make her aboue all the Saints, not onely a mediatrix of interceſſion, but of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion alſo: affirming, that her ſtanding by when the Lord ſuffered vpon the croſſe, full of ſorrow to be hold it, was a ioyning with him in our Redemption: and therefore, where as it is ſaid of Chriſt, <hi>hee ſhall breake the Serpents head,</hi> they turne it <hi>ſhe;</hi> and whereas the Prophet ſaith in his perſon,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>I haue troden the winepreſſe alone, there was no man with me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 63.3.</note> they ſay there was no man indeed, but that bleſſed woman: yea and ſo farre be the Ieſuites gone in their dotage about her meriting, as that they make compariſons betwixt her milke and Chriſts blood, aſcribing as much to the one, as to the other, as appeareth in the booke called, <hi>The Ieſuits Goſpell.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Touching his mediatorſhip, doe they rely vpon any other Mediators;</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Yes that they doe, for they make both the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and all the Saints departed mediators vnto God for them in all their common prayers, deſiring them to pray
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3008:21"/>for them, and ſometimes as though they had the diſpoſing of heauen, that they would conferre vpon them the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Although Chriſt be the onely Mediator of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, yet there are more mediators of interceſſion, for we all muſt pray one for another. It ſeemeth therefore that this doth no more raze the foundation, then deſiring the Elders of the Church to pray for vs in the time of ſickneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>I haue already ſpoken enough to ſhew the error of this practice. It ſhall ſuffice therefore onely to adde thus much more, that this diſtinction betwixt a Mediator of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption &amp; of interceſſion in heauen is vaine: for as Chriſt is the onely <hi>propitiation for our ſinnes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Iohn 2.2. Rom. 8.34.</note> ſo hee onely <hi>at the right hand of God maketh interceſſion for vs.</hi> If any elſe doe the like it is concealed from vs, neither are wee bidden to come by them, but altogether by the Sonne vnto the Father. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, we cannot come by any in heauen vnto God, but wee muſt aſcribe vnto them the diuine attribute of omniſcience<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wherby they know all things though neuer ſo remote from them, which is to rob the Lord of his peculiar honour, as if Maieſty or Supreme power were aſcribed to any of the kings ſubiects.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Proceed new to the laſt point: what doe they hold touching the beginning and proceedings of Grace?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>They teach, that there is in euery man free will, whereby hee can deſire, and doe preparatiue workes vnto grace, which the Lord beholding hath mercy vpon him, and inlargeth him, being before in priſon and bound as it were with chaines, and then hee becommeth able to doe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his deſire, that is, perfectly to fulfill Gods Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, for which he ſhall finally haue the reward of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall glory beſtowed vpon him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And haue they not good ground for this in the example of</hi> Cornelius,<note place="margin">Act. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>whoſe almes and prayers done before his conuerſion were acceptable to God, ſo as that hereupon</hi> Peter <hi>was ſons vnto him, and the holy Ghoſt was beſtowed vpon him?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>God had wrought in the heart of <hi>Cornelius</hi> before this,<note place="margin">Act. 10.2.</note> for hee is ſaid to haue beene <hi>a deuout man and one that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3008:21"/>feared God,</hi> which could not haue been ſpoken of him, if he had been a meere naturall man. Therefore from his example no good argument can be made to proue preparatiue works in naturall men. Hee had doubtleſſe ſo much grace, and knowledge, as was incident to the faithfull before Chriſts comming in the fleſh, onely hee wanted the knowledge of his perſon in particular already come, to preach which, and that withall he might receiue the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Peter</hi> was ſent vnto him,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But how doth this raze the foundation Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe vpon Chriſt all our well deſiring and doing doth depend. We cannot thinke a good thought as of our ſelues, <hi>but all our ſufficiency is of God:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.5. Ioh. 15.5. 1. Cor. 1. Gen. 6.5.</note> and the Lord hath plainly ſaid, <hi>without me ye can doe nothing,</hi> and touching a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man, <hi>the wiſdome of God is fooliſhneſſe vnto him, all the imaginations of his beart are onely euill continually.</hi> To teach that then, whereby a man ſhall bee brought in part to rely vpon himſelfe, is in effect to diſanull Chriſt, the alone ground of our well doing and deſiring.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am well ſatisfied by this, touching your firſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, prouing, that the Roman Church is no true Church of God, me thought you game me an hint of a further reaſon, in ſaying that buildert onely vpon the foundation Chriſt ſhould be ſaued, and not demoliſhers. Can you proue the Romane Catholikes to bee demoliſhers?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>You did not conceiue amiſſe: for this word buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is very notable in the text: Now that they are not builders, but demoliſhers I make it plaine thus: Hee onely buildeth vpon a foundation, that erecteth ſomewhat vpon it, though it bee but ſleighty &amp; weake, but if ſtanding vpon this foundation he breaketh in peeces, and diſanulleth the chiefe materials of the building, he buildeth not but demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſheth. And thus doth the Roman Churh, for bearing her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vpon the foundation Chriſt, ſhe teacheth to tranſgreſſe Gods Commandements, and to proceed contrary to his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, which are the chiefe materialls of the ſpirituall building.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherein doe they commend tranſgreſſing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3008:22"/>againſt Gods Lawes and Ordinances.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>In exciting the people to get them images, and to bow before them in prayer plainly againſt the ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, which they ſeeing into, haue therefore put this commandement out of their Catechiſmes: in appointing the Sacrament of Lords Supper to bee adminiſtred to the people in one kind onely againſt Chriſts inſtitution: in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding the people to read the Scriptures, and commending ignorance, as the mother of deuotion, againſt that expreſſe charge, <hi>ſearch the Scriptures:</hi> in appointing ſeruice in an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne tongue,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.</note> being the repreſentation of <hi>Babel,</hi> that by reaſon of ſtrange tongues could not bee built, for ſo hereby ſuch an vncertaine ſound is made, as that no edification com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of it: in abſoluing ſubiects from their allegeance to their lawfull Prince: in diſpenſing with treaſons, murthers, periuries, and inceſtuous mariages: in maintaining lying, vnder the names of equiuocations and mentall reſeruations: in condemning mariage in ſome ſort of people more then fornication: in exempting the Clergie from the power of the ciuill Magiſtrate, and ſetting vp the Pope aboue all both ſpirituall and temporall things: all which who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not to be flatly againſt Gods Commandements.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yet there are many things wherein they are buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, in that they make many prayers, and condemne drunkenneſſe, pride, vncleanneſſe, oppreſſion, &amp;c. and exhort vnto the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vertues.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Thoſe things which haue beene already ſpoken being ſo, they cannot bee counted builders any more then notorious wicked perſons, who notwithſtanding their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſome good cutward ſeeming things in them, are ſaid to be deſtroyers of the Law; for ſo the Prophet complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.126.</note> 
                  <hi>It is time for thee Lord to put to thy hand, for men deſtroy thy Law.</hi> How is this but by tranſgreſſing? and if ſimply to tranſgreſſe be a deſtroying of the Law, much more to teach and maintaine tranſgreſſing, and to oppoſe and deſtroy ſuch as dare not herein offend God, as the Romaniſts doe by fire and ſword.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I cannot ſee how they can defend themſelves, if
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3008:22"/>theſe be their courſes, but that they muſt come vnder that cenſure.</hi> Hee that breaketh the leaſt of theſe commandements,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.19.</note> and teacheth others to doe ſo, ſhall bee counted the leaſt in the Kingdome of Heauen. <hi>Haue you any thing elſe againſt them to proue that they build not, but demoliſh and deſtroy?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>There is one thing more, which may be reckoned a chiefe thing in this building, and that is faith. For when the foundation Chriſt is rightly laid, it is builded vpon him by faith and loue, theſe in ſhort comprehending the whole edifice: ſo that hee which buildeth theſe two, is indeed a builder, and ſhall be ſaued, though he buildeth withall hay and ſtubble of curious ſpeculations, frothy doctrine, or er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous conceits, about points more myſticall, as his weake iudgement miſ-leadeth him. Now loue is the fulfilling of the Law: and herein I haue ſhewed that the Romaniſts build not, but deſtroy: and as I haue ſhewed touching that, ſo I will further declare, to aching faith, that they build not by teaching it rightly, but deſtroy by putting true faith downe, and bringing in an vnſound and vaine faith?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How ſhall that appeare?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Very eaſily. For a ſound faith is to beleeue ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly, without doubting, in regard of the defects in vs, caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelues vpon Gods mercy in Ieſus Chriſt for ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe he hath promiſed, and is able to effect it. For <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> faith, which is ſet forth for an example of a ſound faith, is thus deſcribed. <hi>He doubted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 4.10.</note> 
                  <hi>neither conſidered the deadneſſe of his owne body, &amp;c.</hi> See the place, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. But they maintaine, that there is no aſſurance to bee had by faith, but onely by hope, to the lift moment of our liues, and that we cannot but be doubtfull, without ſpeciall reuelation, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of out owne corruptions, through which wee may fall away when we haue gone furtheſt in grace, flatly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that which is ſaid to haue beene done by <hi>Abraham</hi> our patterne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>This doth not ſeeme to be a deſtroying of faith, but humilitie for a mans owne vnworthineſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>They pretend humility endeed, but wee bee to that humilitie that denyeth the true inſtrument, which only can
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3008:23"/>helpe vs to heauen, and taketh a counterfeit in ſtead of it. For they teach, that faith is onely to beleeue the things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the holy Scriptures, and that as the Church belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them, without knowing in particular what theſe things are,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.</note> or applying them to a mans owne ſoule in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular. Which if it be true faith, then the deuill hath true faith: for he beleeueth thus, and goeth a little further, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he vnderſtandeth what he beleeueth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is it not then a ſound faith, vnleſſe it be ſtedfast? oh how vncomfortable is this to many poore ſoules that cannot at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to any ſuch certainty?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>It is therefore to be vnderſtood, that though this be the vertue of a ſound faith to aſſure the ſoule; yet it is often a long time, before a beleeuer commeth to this. For euen as the impe muſt ſtand long in the ſtocke, before it cloſeth with it, and becommeth very faſt; ſo this aſſurance commeth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter long experience, and continuance in Chriſt by faith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am reſolued now, that this Romiſh Church greatly erreth and dangerouſly too: but there are many in that Church, that know not the depth of theſe things: but onely beleeue a Purgatorie, and pray for the dead, and beſeech the Saints depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to helpe them, and vſe croſſing, and Holy Water, and receiue the Bread and Wine in the Sacrament, as Chriſts reall body and blood, adoring it therefore with many the like ſuperſtitions. Is there any great danger to them, being ignorantly miſſ-led, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing herein but as they are perſwaded they ought to doe?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>There is no leſſe danger to them,<note place="margin">Deut. 13.</note> then vnto their Leaders, no more then there was vnto ſuch as were ſeduced to idolatry. For as they alſo muſt dye for it without all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialitie: ſo the ſimply miſ-led Papiſt cannot but expect ruine with this Leader,<note place="margin">Math. 15.14.</note> For <hi>if the blind leade the blind, they ſhall both fall into the ditch.</hi> Onely the iudgement of the Leader ſhall be greater, eſpecially if in ſiniſter reſpects, his conſcience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conuicted by the truth, he doth yet perſiſt in vpholding errour, as experience hath taught that many of them haue done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>It ſtandeth with good reaſon that they which wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly preferre errour, ſhould beare the burthen of it: but me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinkes
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3008:23"/>ſuch as are miſ-led by them, following their conſcience, ſhould not periſh: for many of them ſerue God according to their profeſſion with a good heart.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>Errour is of that nature, as that it is damnable in whomſoeuer. Firſt, becauſe it is contrary to truth, which ſanctifieth and maketh free. For ſo the Lord hath prayed,<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.17. Ioh. 8.32.</note> 
                  <hi>Sanctifie them by thy Truth,</hi> and hath pronounced, <hi>the truth ſhall make you free.</hi> Wherefore contrariwiſe errour polluteth and enthralleth, and ſo debarreth from entring heauen,<note place="margin">Reuel. 22.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>no vncleane thing ſhall enter there;</hi> and <hi>the bond-woman ſhall bee caſt out with her children.</hi> Secondly,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.</note> becauſe it is a iudgement vpon thoſe onely that periſh, and are damned; to haue their eyes blinded, and to bee giuen ouer to deluſions, as I haue ſhewed, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.11. Thirdly, becauſe God is truth, and the Deuill is a lyar; and therefore by error the minde is out of the way to God, and can neuer enioy him, but is in the right way to the Deuill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Any one of theſe reaſons is ſufficient to proue their wofull caſe. But may there not be any meanes found out to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile theſe two Religions, by yeelding ſomewhat on both ſides, and by laying aſide auſteritie and ſtrangeneſſe, and by putting on lenity and familiaritie one towards another?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Saul.</speaker>
               <p>In all the particular points of difference I haue made it plaine, that we are in the truth: as therefore if wee would not goe from God, we muſt not go from any of theſe things either in faith, or practice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat were but to yeeld to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company them in the way to perdition, and not to doe any thing aduantageous to their ſoules. Wherefore they muſt yeeld vnto vs, and as we haue already done, come out of this Babel of errours, and ſuperſtitions, if euer they will inioy true peace and comfort to Godward. In the meane ſeaſon, if gentle and perſwaſiue meanes would doe them any good, they haue them in greater meaſure then they could expect, conſidering their forepaſſed cruelty, and rigour: but for familiaritie and boſome friendſhip, it is expreſſely againſt that charge;<note place="margin">Tit. 3.10.</note> 
                  <hi>An Hereticke after once or twice admonition auoid.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I thanke you moſt heartily for this light which you
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3008:24"/>haue giuen vnto me, and I thanke God, who ſent you vnto me, by whoſe grace I reſolue to liue and dye in the faith which you haue declared, and after no other manner to worſhip God. And for this you ſhall no more be called</hi> Saul: <hi>but becauſe I count you my beſt friend in the world, and ſo another very ſelfe, you ſhall be called af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mine owne name</hi> Paul, <hi>becauſe I know not otherwiſe how to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe how nearely to my heart I haue placed you for your good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions this day giuen vnto me.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elymas.</speaker>
               <p>Moſt excellent and worthy Gouernor: I am ſorie to heare that a man of your place, and wiſdome, ſhould haue his eares and minde ſo much abuſed, by the ſeducing words of an Arch-hereticke. Is your Church the onely True Church of God, and is the Church of the Catholikes a falſe Church, or none at all? (Oh God) what will not theſe men perſwade vnto? Is it not manifeſt to all the world, that yee are a company of Heretikes, and Schiſmaticks, and a Church but of yeſterday, or ſince <hi>Luthers</hi> time at the moſt? Was God without a Church, till your faction began? What im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudencie is this to abuſe Noble Gouernours of Countreys thus, by drawing them from the Catholike Church of Rome, that hath euer been famous through the world, for conſtant cleauing to the Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>Thou bewitching Sophiſter, and beguiler of ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſoules, is is knowne to all men, that this is your vſuall falſe ſlander of our Church, and the chiefe ſtring to your Bow: ſo that when yee haue nothing elſe to fay, your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge ſtill is the old Religion, the old Religion: what will ye forſake the old Religion for a new? But to follow you and beat you with your owne weapon. Be it knowne, that the reformed Religion, is the old Religion indeed, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent religion of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> a new religion; of which this noble perſon preſent ſhall be iudge, ſeeing you haue prouoked me to enter theſe liſts with you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elymas.</speaker>
               <p>I am content that either he or any man ſhal iudge herein betweene vs, and if you can proue what you haue ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yd, I will loſe the day.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>I proue it therefore thus. The Religion commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to vs by Gods Spirit in the holy Scriptures is the old
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3008:24"/>Religion; and that whereof men of later times are authors is new in compariſon of it: But the reformed is thus commended to vs, as I haue already fully declared, and the Religion of the preſent Church of Rome is from men of latter times. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elymas.</speaker>
               <p>Neither is the Proteſtant Religion commended in the holy Scriptures, nor the Roman Catholike Religion inuented by man ſince. For, as much as you bragge of the Scriptures, you haue not one plaine ſentence in your owne Bible for any one point of your Religion, without adding, altering or gloſſing vpon it, as is your vſuall manner. And for our Religion, ſhew if you can, when and by whom thoſe points which you call errors, were inuented: for wee hold, that all things haue euer ſince the Apoſtles times been thus.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>I maruell that you and your fellow, whoſoeuer hee was, that wrote the book blaſphemouſly intituled, <hi>The gag for the Goſpell,</hi> are not aſhamed ſo boldly to charge vs, that we haue not one plaine place of Scripture. What is that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Lord, <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him onely ſhalt thou ſerue.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 4.10.</note> Doe not both the words and the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances plainly make for vs, denying to fall downe and worſhip any but God, otherwiſe Chriſt had not ſpoken ſo <hi>appoſitè</hi> to Satan, bidding him to fall downe and worſhip him. What is that command? <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen image, &amp;c.</hi> And againe,<note place="margin">Deut. 4.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Take good heed vnto your ſelues, for ye ſaw no manner of ſimilitude on the day that the Lord ſpake vnto you in</hi> Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eb, <hi>leſt you corrupt your ſelues, and make you a grauen image, the ſimilitude of any figure, &amp;c.</hi> What is this ſaying? <hi>There is one God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.4. 2. Cor. 3.5. Phil. 2.13.</note> 
                  <hi>and one Mediator betwixt God and man, the man Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> and this, <hi>Wee are not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient of our ſelues to thinke a good thought as of our ſelues:</hi> and this, <hi>God worketh in you the will and the deed of his own good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure;</hi> with many more text<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> before alleaged, which I ſpare to repeat; So that we may moſt truely affirme, that there is no one tenent of our Church, but we haue a plaine place of Scripture for it: but it may truly be retorted vpon you, that you haue not one plaine place for any one of your tenents or practices, ſo that ye are faine miſerably to wreſt and ſtraine
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3008:25"/>any text hence alledged, and when that will not doe, to fly to Apochryphall bookes, traditions, and ridiculous fables.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elym.</speaker>
               <p>Are all theſe ſayings in your Bible, if they bee, it is more then I know, but ſure I am, that there are ſentences plainly teaching the ſame that we doe. For what elſe is that ſaying of our Sauiour; <hi>This is my body,</hi> and, <hi>my fleſh is meat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and blood, drinke indeed:</hi> and, <hi>vpon this rocke will I build my Church:</hi> and, <hi>to thee will I giue the Keyes of the Kingdome of heauen:</hi> and againe, Peter <hi>feed my ſheepe.</hi> And touching the Church,<note place="margin">Math. 18.17. 1 Tim 3.15.</note> 
                  <hi>If he heareth not the Church, let him be to thee as an Ethnicke:</hi> and, <hi>the Church is the ground and pillar of truth.</hi> Touching other points we need none other Scripture, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Church it is promiſed;<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.13.</note> 
                  <hi>When he is come which is the ſpirit of truth, he will lead you into all truth.</hi> Wherefore the Church cannot erre, and whatſoeuer is by her propounded, as matter of faith, or practice, muſt needs then be right: But bee it knowne vnto you, that wee want not plaine places for particular points. Touching iuſtification.<note place="margin">Iam. 2.24.</note> 
                  <hi>A man is not iuſtified by faith onely, but by workes.</hi> Touching prayer for the dead. <hi>There is a ſinne vnto death, I ſay not, that yee ſhould pray for it.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.16. Iam. 5.14. Luke 7.47. Math. 25.</note> Touching extreame vnction. <hi>They ſhall pray for him and anoint him in the name of the Lord.</hi> Touching the merit of workes. <hi>Many ſinnes are forgiuen her, becauſe ſhee hath loued much:</hi> and, <hi>Come ye bleſſed, &amp;c. for I was hungry, and yee fed me, &amp;c.</hi> For time would faile me, if I ſhould go on to alleage all the places, that plainly make for vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>You doe well ſo to ſlieglit our euidences brought out of the holy Scriptures, becauſe they are ſo plaine, that they cannot bee anſwered; neither indeed doe your ſect much acquaint your ſelues with the Bible: for there are ſome ſtudents in Diuinity of many yeares, that neuer read the Bible. To your places therefore: How doth the ſpeech of our Sauiour make for Tranſubſtantiation, without alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or adding? It is meat indeed, we confeſſe, but he ſaith not, is meat for the body, nor yet in explaining himſelf after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards hath he one word intimating a bodily ſubſtance that he would giue to be fed vpon, but the clean contrary, for he ſaith,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.63.</note> 
                  <hi>the fleſh profiteth nothing, my words are ſpirit and life.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3008:25"/>for thoſe ſayings vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> there is nothing plaine for <hi>Peters</hi> ſupremacy, for his bearing vp all, as a foundation, and much leſſe for his pretended ſucceſſours the Biſhops of <hi>Rome.</hi> For plainly to teach theſe things had beene to haue ſaid, vpon thee and thy ſucceſſours will I build my Church, and to thee and to him that ſhall ſucceed thee in thy Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke at <hi>Rome,</hi> I will giue authority ouer all others. But ſo far is the Lord from this, that when there was iuſt, occaſion offered vpon the motion of the mother of <hi>Zebedees</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to declare the ſupreme, &amp; when they contended about it amongſt themſelues, hee ſpeaketh no word to ſettle the ſupremacy vpon any one, but altogether to ſtop the mouth of any from once challenging it. But I haue ſpoken ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently of this before, ſo that I ſhall not need to adde any thing about his commiſſion to feed his ſheepe. It is maruaile that when all chiefe points of faith are ſo plainely expreſſed, that this which is ſo much ſtood vpon, as inferiour to none, ſhould be ſo obſcurely paſſed ouer. Touching the Church there is nothing plainely ſpoken, that it ſhall be alwayes vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, but onely it may be implyed, that as long as there are Chriſtians to doe thoſe mutuall offices of reproouing one another for ſinne, there ſhall be a diſcipline exerciſed in the Church how corrupt ſoeuer, for the chaſtiſement of ſuch as are complained of, as manifeſt tranſgreſſors of the Law the iuſt proceedings whereof, notwithſtanding the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are of force to the terror of malefactors. For that ſaying, <hi>tell the Church,</hi> at that time had reference to a moſt corrupt Church of Scribes and Phariſees, whoſe authority was yet by the Lord eſtabliſhed, ſaying,<note place="margin">Math. 23.1.</note> 
                  <hi>whatſoeuer they bid you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, that obſerue and doe.</hi> So that from hence nothing more can be rightly taught, no not by inference, but that there ſhall alwayes be ſome viſible Church good or bad, which we alſo acknowledge. But in caſe that there bee two ſuch Churches together, who doubteth forſaking that which is corrupt, to goe to the beſt and ſoundeſt. Touching error, from which you ſeeke to exempt your Church, becauſe the Church is called <hi>the gound and pillar of truth,</hi> what is this to the preſent Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the ſinke of moſt groſſe errors
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3008:26"/>and ſuperſtitions. The true Church indeed, ſuch as it was in thoſe dayes founded <hi>vpon the Prophets and Apoſtles, Chriſt himſelfe being the chiefe corner ſlone,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.20.</note> was the ground of truth, becauſe therein the truth was preſerued and vpheld, and whereſoeuer it is ſo at this day, that Church is likewiſe <hi>the ground and pillar of truth.</hi> But it doth not neceſſarily follow, that whereſoeuer the Church is, whether ſound or corrupt, it is the ground of truth, for ſo much as the truth held and eleaued vnto in all things maketh the Church the <hi>pillar and ground of truth,</hi> and not the Church that to be true whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhe ſhall think good to propound. For otherwiſe Chriſt, the Prophets &amp; Apoſtles, with their dictates, inſtitutions, and writings ſhould not bee a ground vnto men ſucceeding and inferiour to them, but theſe men ſhould bee a ground vnto them, which were abſurd. And the ſame I anſwer to that promiſe of the ſpirit, it was peculiar to the Apoſtles and ſpecial inſtruments ſtirred vp for thoſe times, to be ſo guided into all truth, as not to erre, becauſe what came from them was to bee a ground to the faithfull in all ſucceeding ages, and it is moſt palpably wreſted to your Church now. And if your fundamentall places be thus impertinently alledged, the reſt will fall without any labour, at the leaſt (moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>Sergius</hi>) you may be able to iudge hereof by that, which hath beene already ſpoken in laying open the faith of the reformed Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>When theſe places were firſt alledged by</hi> Elymas, <hi>I thought it impoſſible to anſwer them and therefore did begin to incline to thinke better of the Roman Church, then you had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded me: but now I ſee that they are but the painting and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louring of a deformed face, being without all true beauty. And for the places omitted, I haue them ſo freſhly in my memory, ſince you reſolued them vnto me, at that I am fully reſelued, that they are but wreſted and wrung by the aduerſary to ſorne his turne.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elym.</speaker>
               <p>But by your fauour (ſir) nothing hath yet beene ſayd to one place plainly diſtinguiſhing betwixt veniall and mortall ſinnes, and concluding prayer for ſome dead, <hi>viz.</hi> that ſinne not vnto death, but are penitent, before they dye.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:3008:26"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>You doe well to recall that againe, which I thought not worth the anſwering. How can it be ſpoken of mortall and veniall ſinnes? Is he that hath ſinned a mortall ſinne to be giuen ouer then, as a deſperate Reprobate, and not to bee prayed for any more? What is this, but to condemne <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe, and <hi>Dauid,</hi> and <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> &amp;c. as vnworthy to bee prayed for? If your diſtinction of mortall and veniall ſinnes haue no better ground but this, it is ſet vp altogether vpon the ſands. And for praying for any dead, nothing can bee more abſurd, then to alledge this: for he doth not note out the time of continuing, or breaking off from ſinne, as making his caſe that hath ſinned, deſperate, or reparable by the prayers of others, by reaſon of this circumſtance, but plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in it ſelfe, for hee ſaith, <hi>There is a ſinne vnto death.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>There is a ſinne not vnto death;</hi> that is, in plaine Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, there is a ſinne, which who ſo committeth it, ſhall dye therefore, without all hope of life, whatſoeuer prayers ſhould be made for him: but there is ſinne alſo, the proper ſequell and wages whereof is death; yet not ſo neceſſarily, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and life may be obtained notwithſtanding. And if it be taken in this ſenſe, there is the conſent of other places to confirme it, as that. All ſinnes ſhall bee forgiuen to the ſonnes of men, but he that ſinneth againſt the Holy Ghoſt, ſhall neuer bee forgiuen, of ſuch a ſinne <hi>Saul</hi> ſeemeth to haue beene guilty, when the Lord forbiddeth <hi>Samuel</hi> to pray any more for him. But take it of praying for ſuch as dye repeneantly, and where can you finde any to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I ſee it is in vaine for you</hi> (Elymas) <hi>to hold argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with him any longer by the teſtimonies of holy Scripture: preceed therefore to your plea of antiquitie, for therein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> may happen to put him downe indeed.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>It muſt needs bee ſo (Sir) as you haue ſaid; for whatſoeuer flouriſhes they make, their conſcience telleth them, that the Scriptures are againſt them, ſeeing they can no more abide them, then the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tle the day-light. Why elſe doe they keep them lockt vp in an vnknowne tongue? Why doe they condemne our tranſlations, as hereticall, and allow
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3008:27"/>onely of <hi>Ieromes</hi> tranſlation: for it were a mad part for them to condemne and forbid that, which maketh on their ſide. This their cracking therefore of the Scriptures is but a fruit of their late impudency, putting them on to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the proofe of any thing, that can bepropounded. But they are very confident, that we cannot demonſtrate in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular the time and perſons, when and by whom their falſe doctrines were broached, and their ſuperſtitions brought in, yet I feare as little to enter the liſts with him about this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, as about the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elymas.</speaker>
               <p>And I doubt not but to put you to ſhame enough in ſo doing: for the moſt ancient Orthodoxe Fathers of the Church haue alwayes taught the ſame that wee doe; and haue often mentioned the particulars of our deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which yee falſly call ſuperſtition. Which being ſo, I weigh not all your places of Scripture, if you had as many more; nor your colourable anſwers to ſuch as haue beene by mee alledged: for the cuſtomes of the Church, and traditions deliuered from age to age, are of the ſame authoritie with the holy Scriptures; and they are rather to bee regulated hereby, as being certaine, then theſe by them, ſpeaking as euery man liſteth to wreſt and turne them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>It is a falſe ſlander by you laid vpon the Scriptures, that they are vncertaine, and a burthening of Chriſtian peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for which you ſhall anſwere, to obtrude traditions thus vnto them, as I haue before declared. To paſſe that ouer therefore here. Who can tell, whether the ancient Fathers in thoſe paſſages, wherein they haue made ſome mention of ſome practices by you vſed, were made to ſpeake ſo by ſome audacious forger, ſeeing there are ſo many ſuppoſititious writings falſly fathered vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo many imaginary Fathers, that neuer were in <hi>rerum natura,</hi> and ſuch purging and altering of ancient Writings hath beene made of late by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Councell of <hi>Trent.</hi> Moreouer, it is poſſible that through the neglect of Hiſtorians, or wittingly in fauour of your abuſes, the originall and firſt ſpringing vp of them may be concealed. But if not, few men are read in Hiſtory, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3008:27"/>is hiſtory reading neceſſary to ſaluation; and therefore it maketh not any whit the more on your ſide, though they cannot preciſely ſet downe, when and by whom your here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and ſuperſtitions were brought in: euen as Mahume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme were no whit the more approueable, though the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall thereof were vnknowne. For by this reaſon the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then prieſts of old ſought to maintaine the credit of their idolatries, challenging the Chriſtians for imbracing a new Religion. It is a poore ſhift, when any thing is particularly diſproued by the Word of God, to cauill about the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it, as if the day were loſt, if that could not be done: for if the leakes of a Ship, or the decayes of an Houſe be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant, if corruptions within, or blemiſhes vpon the bodie be made manifeſt: what auaileth it to approue that they are no decayes or blemiſhes, by pleading, But can any man tell, when theſe firſt began?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elym.</speaker>
               <p>Our errours, as you call them, are not ſo euident yet, as your compariſons. If you cannot therefore ſhew their beginning, it is plaine, that they were deliuered from the Apoſtles, and it is hereſie and impiety in you to impugne them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>Doth the ſame fountaine ſend forth ſalt water and ſweet? Doth the ſame mouth ſpeake contradictories? for ſo certaine is it, that theſe things cannot bee deriued from the Apoſtles, ſeeing they are altogether againſt them. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you vige it ſo much, I will ſet downe the time and age of euery part of your Religion, that the nouelty of it may appeare to all the world. And firſt I will begin with the chiefe and head of all your errours the Popes headſhip. This was firſt eſtabliſhed in a Councell at <hi>Rome</hi> of ſeuenty two Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, thirty Presbyters, and three Deacons, in the time of <hi>Boniface</hi> the third, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 607.<note place="margin">Plat. in vita Boniſ. 3.</note> being then obtained of <hi>Phocas,</hi> who came to the Empire by murthering <hi>Mauritius,</hi> his Maſter: and therefore to prouide the better for himſelfe, he was willing by granting the ſupremacie ouer all, to ioyne vnto him the Pope of Rome.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Conc. Conſtant.</hi> the eight gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councell.</note> Afterwards there was a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell held at Conſtantinople, in the dayes of Pope <hi>Adrian,</hi> vnder <hi>Baſilius</hi> the Emperour, who ſlew his aſſociate <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3008:28"/>Anno Dom.</hi> 871. Wherein none were admitted, but ſuch as ſubſcribed to the Popes Supremacie: for <hi>Adrian</hi> had curried fauour with murthering <hi>Baſili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> as <hi>Boniſace</hi> had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore done with <hi>Phocas.</hi> Laſtly, there was a Councell at Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the dayes of <hi>Gregory</hi> the tenth, vnder the Reigne of <hi>Michael Paleologus</hi> Emperor, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1273, wherein the Emperour confirmed the Popes Supremacie, that he might the more ſtrengthen himſelfe by him alſo: for he was an v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurper, and murtherer, by the ſlaughter of <hi>Theodorus</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his cuſtodie attaining to the Empire. Hee was ſo abhorred by the Grecians for yeelding herein to <hi>Gregorie,</hi> that when he was dead, they would not ſuffer his body to be buried amongſt other Chriſtians. Neither was this ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prerr acie ſet vp by any but theſe perſons infamous for mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, except <hi>Pipin</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> his ſonne, who attained the Kingdome of <hi>France,</hi> by the depoſition of <hi>Chelpericke</hi> the lawfull King.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elym.</speaker>
               <p>Are you not aſhamed thus to ſeeke to blindfold mens eyes? Did not <hi>Constanine</hi> the Great, long before this, finding that of right the primacie belonged to Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Chaire,<note place="margin">Socr. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> eſtabliſh it in the councell of Nice? And was not <hi>Iulius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> appointed by the Sardian Councel to be iudge of appeales? <hi>Anno</hi> 35<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. And did not the Biſhops of Rome long before <hi>Boniface,</hi> exerciſe their iuriſdiction in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Patriarkes? and were they not acknowledged by the ancient Doctors to be ſupreme?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>You may well be aſhamed, I am ſure, once to ſpeake of the Councell of Nice, ſeeing the Popes plea founded here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, was ſo fully diſproued in the ſixt African Councell aſſembled at Carthage,<note place="margin">Hiſt. Magd. Cent. <hi>5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Anno 'Dom.</hi> 402. in the dayes of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norius</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the ſecond, conſiſting of 217 Biſhops, laſting ſixe yeares together. For thither did both <hi>Sozimus, Boniface,</hi> and <hi>Celeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nus,</hi> Popes, ſend their Legates, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring to haue the Supremacie confirmed, according to the Councell of Nice: the Decrees of that Councell were ſearcht, the Copies of them kept in the Regiſter of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> and <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> were ſent for, and, no ſuch thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>und, it was decreed, that no appeale ſhould hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3008:28"/>be made from Africa to Rome, and this plea was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, as a forgery. And in a councell ſomewhat before this at <hi>Meliuis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> it was decreed, that no man ſhould make appellation to Biſhops beyond the ſea, but in caſe his owne Biſhop did him wrong, hee ſhould appeale to a councell of African Biſhops. In the third African or Carth: Councell it was decreed, that the Biſhop of Rome ſhould be called the Biſhop of the firſt ſeat, but not the High Prieſt, or Prince of Prieſts, <hi>Anno</hi> 399. In the ſixt Conſtantinopolitan councell, <hi>Anno</hi> 681 vnder <hi>Conſtantius, Pegonatus, Pope Sergius</hi> his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate being preſent, and ſubſcribing, it was decreed,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that the Patriarke of Conſtantinople was of equall authoritie with the Biſhop of Rome, though <hi>Sergius</hi> being offended, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed afterwards to ſubſcribe. I could reckon vp many more paſſages in councels, and worthy authors writings, and preachings, of ancient times, plainely oppugning the Popes ſupremacie, but theſe ſhall ſuffice. Touching <hi>Iulius,</hi> hee was a worthy Prclate and protector of the wronged, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo ſet vp in the Sardian Councell, intending the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of his perſon, not of his Sea. For the exerciſe of this iuriſdiction, and learned mens aſcriptions, you know, that <hi>à facto ad ins non valet conſequentia;</hi> and in the moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned being vnder the Biſhop of Rome there might be ſome flatterie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I did not thinke, but that the Biſhop of Rome bad euer been High Prieſt ouer all the Clergie, but it ſeemed euer to me an vſurpation in him to domincre ouer Kings and Emperors: but now I perceiue that this ſupremacie euen ouer the Clargie is but a crazie foundation, with much tugging and oppoſition, in time climbed vp into; ſo that there is enough ſpoken to diſproue his principalitie ouer Kings alſo, ſeeing this yeeldeth an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> à minore ad maius. <hi>Proceed therefore to ſome other point.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>After the Supremacy, images were brought into the Church to be worſhipped, againſt which the Emperor <hi>Leo</hi> ſetting himſelfe, ſent his Mandate to Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the third to aboliſh them. <hi>Gregory</hi> calleth a great Councell at Rome, about <hi>Anno</hi> 720, wherein the Emperour was therefore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3008:29"/>&amp; depriued, &amp; together with him <hi>Anaſtatius</hi> Patriarke of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> But ſoon after <hi>Conſtantinus Copro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nus</hi> called a Councell in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> of 338 Biſhops, <hi>Anno</hi> 755, wherein all ſetting vp and worſhipping of images is condemned as heatheniſh: and the Fathers writing againſt them are alledged: as <hi>Epiphanius, Euſebius, Gregorius Theel. Athanaſius, Amphilochius, Chryſoſtomus</hi> and <hi>Theodorus A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyra.</hi> After this there was a Councell held at <hi>Nice</hi> in <hi>Bythi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> vnder <hi>Irene</hi> mother to <hi>Conſtantine, Anno</hi> 788, who moſt vnnaturally put out her ſonnes eyes, and ſo made him to end his dayes in miſery: in which aſſembly of 350 Biſhops, it was decreed, that the images of Chriſt, and of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> ſhould not onely be ſet vp in places of adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but alſo be adored, and wo ſhipped, becauſe the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of an Image doth redound to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m, that is there by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented. But marke vpon what grounds chiefely they proceeded thus. Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> wrote his Letters, wherein he telleth, how <hi>Conſtantine</hi> being a Leper, and aduiſed to bathe himſelfe in the blood of children, which he was loth to do, had an apparition of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> bidding him ſend for <hi>Sylueſter</hi> the Pope; who comming to him, and by the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of theſe two holy Apoſtles which he had; making known to <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> (that at the fight of them, ſaid, theſe were they) who had appeared to him, hee baptized him, and his Leproſie was cleanſed. Now all this is a meere fable, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by <hi>Euſebius,</hi> who writing the life of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> ſheweth that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> was alwayes free from Leproſie, and baptized by <hi>Euſebius</hi> it. <hi>Nicomedia.</hi> Another great motiue to them to ſtand for images, was a fooliſh tale of a Monke, who ſaid that the Deuill tempted him continually to vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and would not ceaſe, vnleſſe hee did giue ouer wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping the image of the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> The worſhipping of images was againe confirmed at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> in the time of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rian</hi> the ſecond, Pope of Rome, <hi>Baſilius</hi> being Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. But betweene theſe two Councels, there was one held at <hi>Frankfort,</hi> by the appointment of <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, <hi>Anno</hi> 794, to which the Popes Legates came and offered the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the laſt Councell of Nice to be confirmed: but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3008:29"/>ſomething in the Councell of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> againſt images vvere diſliked; namely, the forbidding of them to be made, yet the Decree of that <hi>Nicene</hi> Councell touching the worſhipping of image<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was more condemned, and that therefore iudged worthy the name neither of a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, or <hi>Occumenicke</hi> Councell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elymas.</speaker>
               <p>You are greatly miſtaken to referre the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of images in the Church to the time of Pope <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> the third: for then the hereticall Emperour attempted the aboliſhing of them, which argueth, that they were in vſe long before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>They were in vſe indeed amongſt Heretikes, ſuch as <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> of whom <hi>Theodoret,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> report, that he offered his owne, and the image of his Concubine to be worſhipped; and the <hi>Cretians</hi> ſo much ſpoken againſt by Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Titus,</hi> are ſaid by <hi>Ierome</hi> to bee the firſt that brought images into the Church,<note place="margin">Iren. lib. <hi>2</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> and the filthy <hi>Gneſticks</hi> worſhipped the image of Chriſt: but Catholike Doctors haue euer anciently inueighed againſt them. <hi>Euſebius</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Neoceſarea</hi> ſaith, that it commeth from the Heathen: for <hi>Heliogabilus, Alexander Seuerus,</hi> and <hi>Adrianus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Enſeb. lib. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>18</hi>
                  </note> Heathen Emperours, had firſt the images of <hi>Abraham, Moſes,</hi> and Chriſt in their Chappels.<note place="margin">Epipb. Epiſt. ad Iob. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Epiphanius</hi> wrote an Epiſtle to <hi>Iohn</hi> Biſhop of Ieruſalem, againſt the bringing of images into Churches; and he is famous for renting in pieces an image painted vpon a cloth, behinde a Church doore: and long agoe in a Councell held at <hi>Eliberis</hi> a towne of Spaine,<note place="margin">Can. 36. Can. 60.</note> it was decreed, that nothing that is worſhipped ſhould bee pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured on a wall; and if any were ſlaine in breaking images down, he ſhould be put into the Catalogue of Martyrs. This Councell was in the time of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great. In the Councell of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> before ſpoken of, many ſentences of the Fathers were alledged againſt images, amongſt which that of <hi>Euſebius Pamphili</hi> is moſt remarkable. <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> the Empreſſe had ſent vnto him for the image of Chriſt, vpon which occaſion hee write<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h thus vnto her. I would gladly know, what image of Chriſt you inquire for, if it be of the true, and vnchangeable nature bearing the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3008:30"/>and ingrauen ſimilitude of the Father, I hope that you are ſufficiently inſtructed, that as no man knoweth the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, except the Sonne; ſo no man knoweth the Sonne, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Father. If it be the image of the ſhape of a ſeruant vndertaken for our ſakes: vnderſtand that the ſplendor and ſhining brightneſſe of his glory, cannot be repreſented with dead colours: for euen the Diſciples on the Mountaine were not able to abide the brightneſſe of his ſhining face; how much leſſe are we able to abide the celeſtiall ſplendor of his glorified body?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elymas.</speaker>
               <p>All this is onely againſt the worſhipping of ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which we doe not, but only haue them for remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, knowing alſo, that an image cannot repreſent perfectly the diuinitie, but put vs in minde of him, that ſometime ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in this ſhape.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>Indeed ſo you make your ſeduced in England be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue: but in your ſecond <hi>Nicene</hi> Councell their worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping was decreed, which made the <hi>Frankfort</hi> Councell ſo much diſtaſte their proceedings. <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> in that <hi>Nicene</hi> Councell ſaid: I worſhip the holy ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges with the ſame worſhip, wherwith I worſhip the conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall Trinitie. And <hi>Iohn</hi> the Legate of the Eaſt; The I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the King is the King, and ſo the image God is God: and therefore if any man worſhippeth it with the ſame wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, he ſinneth not. And the chiefe pillars of the Romane Church ſince. <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſpeake to the ſame effect.<note place="margin">Aquin. Tom <hi>3.</hi> qu. <hi>25.</hi> crtic. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> The one faith; Becauſe the Croſſe repreſenteth Chriſt, who is God, it is alſo to be worſhipped with diuine worſhip.<note place="margin">Bell. de Eccleſia triumph. l. <hi>2.6.2.</hi>
                  </note> The other ſaith, that images are properly to bee worſhipped. And vnto them we may ioyne a third ſpeaking in the name of all,<note place="margin">Azor. lib. <hi>9</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Azorias,</hi> who ſaith. It is the conſtant opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of our diuines, that the image is to be worſhipped with the ſame worſhip that the thing repreſented by it. In a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell held at <hi>London, An.</hi> 712, the chiefe ground, whereupon they proceeded for images, was the tale of a certaine Monk, <hi>Eguuinus,</hi> who affirmed vpon oath, that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared vnto him in a dreame, &amp; declared that it was her wil, that her image ſhould be ſet vp in Churches &amp; worſhipped.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:3008:30"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>It ſeemeth, that here in England they are aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the doctrine of worſhipping Images; and therefore they ſeeke to hide what their Church holdeth herein: and good reaſon, if the patrons of image-worſhipping bee conſidered: for if I haue obſerued you aright, there haue beene none but infamous perſons, Irene, and Baſilius for murder, the Pope of Rome for ambition, and ſuperſtitious Monkes blindly leading on the blind to the venerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of images by their fables. Enough therefore hath beene ſayd of this point, proceed now to ſome other.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>The next ſhall bee the ſingle life of men in holy Orders, becauſe there was much trouble about this at the ſame time that images were in queſtion. For in <hi>England</hi> at a Councell held at <hi>Canterbury</hi> Anno 975, there was great queſtion about it: but <hi>Dunſtan</hi> then Archbiſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> handled the matter ſo, that when it was likely to haue gone againſt him, who ſtood for a prohibition of mariage, there was a voice heard from a Crucifixe ſtanding there, that <hi>Dunſtans</hi> opinion was beſt, and thereupon they decreed againſt mariage of men in holy orders.<note place="margin">Hiſt. Magd. Cent. <hi>10.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> But at their next meeting <hi>Falihodus</hi> a Scot learnedly proued by the holy Scriptures that mariage was lawfull for all men, and ſo their minds were againe altered taking that voice to come from the Deuill and not from God, who cannot bee contrary to himſelfe. And after this, <hi>Anno</hi> 1060, Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſent one <hi>Damianus</hi> to hold a Councell at <hi>Millan,</hi> who condemned theſe mariages as the hereſie of the <hi>Nicolaitans:</hi> whereupon a great tumult in the City followed. And after this at <hi>Erfurd,</hi> Anno 1074, a Councell was called by the Archbiſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> commanded ſo to doe by <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeuenth, Pope, to which came many maried Prieſts prouing the lawfulneſſe of their mariages, and vrging the ancient practice of Clergy-men: but when they no whit preuailed, the Archbiſhop preſſing them to put away their wiues, they went out, and through great diſcontent meditated his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, whereof he being aware, fled for that time from the Councell. The next yeare being againe commanded, and the Popes Legate being preſent, he attempted the ſame buſineſſe againe at <hi>Mentz:</hi> but the Prieſts being aſſenibled,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3008:31"/>ſo terrified them both with clapping their hands, and with a vehement commotion of their bodies, that they fled away for their liues, neither durſt hee euer after aſſemble any more Councell to that end.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elym.</speaker>
               <p>You doe well to pitch vpon theſe later times wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Prieſts were growne more carnall and licentious: for you might if it pleaſed you, haue found out Councells long before theſe, determining againſt Prieſts mariage without any tumult. The 2 Carthag: Councell vnder <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Anno</hi> 380, forbad the mariage of Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons, and in ſuch as were already maried, an abſtinence from matrimoniall ſociety. A Councell held at <hi>Altiſſidorum</hi> in <hi>France, Anno</hi> 613. ratifyed the ſame decree. And the 4 Councell of <hi>Tolledo</hi> in <hi>Spaine, Anno</hi> 639, ordained, that when Prieſts and Deacons are admitted to their offices they ſhould vow chaſtity. Yea it was a thing ſo generally receiued euen from the Apoſtles times, as that till of late yeares all were ſingle without contradiction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>That is a notorious lye. For in the firſt Councell after the Apoſtles times, which was held at <hi>Ancyra</hi> in <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia Anno</hi> 308, it was ordained, that Deacons p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ofeſſing at the time of their ordination that they had not the gift of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency, might afterwards marry. And in the Councell of <hi>Nice, Anno</hi> 330, the mariage of ſuch as were in holy orders comming in queſtion againe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Socrat. Lib.</hi> 1.6, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Paphnutim</hi> Biſhop of a towne in <hi>Thebaids</hi> being himſelfe ſingle, ſo perſwaded to leaue eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man to his owne liberty, that nothing was then conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt theſe mariages. And in the 2 Councell of <hi>Tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi> it was ordained,<note place="margin">Con. Toll. Con. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> as in the <hi>Ancyran</hi> Councell before. Now I pitcht vpon later times, becauſe then the debating of the queſtion is ſet forth, and vpon what grounds your Church proceeded, which is omitted in Councels foregoing. But I am glad, that you can goe no higher in this point, then the ſecond Carthag: Councell, wherein neither were their mariages condemned, but continency commended; ſo that we haue two Councels before you, that left mariage free to all men that could not containe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>You haue ſaid enough touching this matter, and it
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3008:31"/>is moſt likely, that the Dewill ſpake in the Councell of</hi> Canter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ury <hi>on</hi> Dunſtans <hi>ſide againſt Pruſts mariages, becauſe as I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, you ſhewed me before, that to forbid mariage is the doctrine of Denils. Proceed therefore to ſome other point.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>The reall preſence ſo much ſtood vpon ſhall bee the next. This was neuer determined, nor the word tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation heard of, till the Councell of <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eran,</hi> vnder Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, <hi>Anno</hi> 1215, and the Councell held at <hi>Rome</hi> vnder <hi>Leo</hi> the ninth, <hi>Anno</hi> 1050 againſt <hi>Berenga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> who ſeeing that ſuch an opinion began to take place, impugned it, and was therefore condemned; and in another Councell vnder Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> the ſecond, brought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, but hee afterwards wrote againe to iuſtifie the ſame truth, and to ſhew his repentance for his recantation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elym.</speaker>
               <p>Herein you doe notoriouſly abuſe the world. It is true indeed, that before <hi>Berengarius</hi> his oppoſition, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no man withſtood the doctrine of tranſubſtantiation it was not in a Councell determined. But doth it follow therefore, that it was not before this time maintained? Haue not all the Fathers that liued before, from time to time, as they had occaſion to treat of the Maſſe, taught with one conſent, a ſecret conuerſion by the Prieſts conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration. <hi>Ambr.</hi> vſeth the very word conuerſion &amp; mutation.<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> de ſacram. v. <hi>4.</hi> Hom. <hi>5.</hi> de Paſcale.</note> 
                  <hi>Euſeb. Emiſſenus</hi> ſayth, that the Prieſt by a ſecret power doth turne the viſible creatures into the ſubſtance of Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy &amp; blood: what ſhould I here reckon vp more? <hi>Bellarmine</hi> hath numbred 32 Fathers ſpeaking to the ſame effect.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>Although the Fathers doe vſe the words conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, mutation, and making, yet it is true, that I ſayd before, they neuer taught tranſubſtantiation: yea after that <hi>Leo</hi> the ninth and his Councell had condemned <hi>Berengarius, Peter Lombard</hi> one of your Schoole-men, that liued <hi>Anno</hi> 1145,<note place="margin">Lombard. Sent. <hi>1.4.</hi> diſt. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> ſcanning vpon this conuerſion, ſaith, If it be enquired what manner of conuerſion it is, whether formall or ſubſtantiall, or of any other kind, I am not able to define. And after the determination of the <hi>Lateran</hi> Councell, diuers others of your learnedeſt Schoolc-men haueing enuouſly acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, that the faith of the tranſubſtantiation is founded only
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3008:32"/>vpon the determination of the Church: as <hi>Scot. in</hi> 4. <hi>Diſt.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 3, <hi>art.</hi> 1. and <hi>Bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llect</hi> 41. <hi>in Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Miſſe. Petr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> de A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aco in</hi> 4 <hi>Sem. qu.</hi> 5. <hi>art.</hi> 2. <hi>Conc.</hi> 2. with diuers others. To thoſe ſayings of the Fathers I anſwer, that they meant not any alteration of the ſubſtance of the bread &amp; wine, but that it ſtill remaining, they became in a wonderfull manner Chriſts very body and blood to the faithfull receiuer. For thus <hi>Ambroſe</hi> expreſſeth himſelfe,<note place="margin">Amb. de ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ram. <hi>1.4.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ial. <hi>2.</hi> Gel: in Eutych.</note> ſaying, <hi>They are the things which they were, and are changed into another thing:</hi> And <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoret</hi> ſaith, <hi>Theſe myſticall ſignes doe not g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> from their nature after their ſanctification.</hi> And <hi>Gelaſius</hi> againſt <hi>Eutychcs</hi> ſaith; <hi>The ſignes remaine in the propriety of their nature.</hi> And <hi>Dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marus,</hi> that liued about <hi>An.</hi> 800, writing vpon theſe words; '<hi>Doe this in remembrance of mee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Drutb in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iet. <hi>26.</hi>
                  </note> ſaith, <hi>the Lord turning the bread ſpiritually into his body, &amp; the wine into his blood hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded vs to do the ſame, that hereby we might remember what he hath done for vs. Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Lord doubted not to ſay, This is my body,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. Cont. Adim. c. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>when he game a ſigne of his body.</hi> I could alſo reckon vp many more, who haue taught, that the very bread in the Sacrament is Chriſts body, and not ſome other ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance vnd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r the appearance of bread: as <hi>Iren. Iuſt in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, Cyprian, Chryſoſtome, Origen, Nazianzen, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elym.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe are your ſhiſts: for though you bee vrged with places and ſayings moſt plaine, you will ſtill haue ſome euaſion or other. Is it likely, that if tranſubſtantiation, though not in word, yet in effect had not beene generally receiued before <hi>Leo,</hi> or the <hi>Latoran</hi> Councell, that all the world without any oppoſition, but onely of one <hi>Berengarius</hi> would haue at once yeelded vnto it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>I wonder that you can without bluſhing ſpeake of ſuch a generall conſent of all, when as the whole Greeke Church withſtood it tooth and nayle: for howſoener they agreed vnto the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in other things, yet in this point, ſuch as were preſent of them at the Councell of <hi>Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> vnder <hi>Eugenius</hi> the 4, <hi>Anno</hi> 1439, could neuer bee brought to conſent: yet becauſe <hi>Eugenius</hi> was deſirous of a conſent for the credit of his Sea, hauing drawne them to ſubſcribe to his ſupremacy, the proceeding of the Holy
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3008:32"/>Ghoſt, the vſe of vnleauened bread in the ſacrament, and to Purgatory, he cauſed a Bull to be publiſhed, called <hi>Bulla con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſus,</hi> notwithſtanding their conſtant oppoſition in the point of tranſubſtantiation; but euen in other things, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they yeelded, ſuch diſtaſt was taken at them by the reſt of the Greeke Churches at their returne home, that they were publikely execrated therefore, and prohibited Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian buriall. And for others, that opinion of the Spirits gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Church in the truth did ſo preuaile with them, as that they yeelded to tranſubſtantiation becauſe it was in the <hi>Lateran</hi> Councell determined, as appeareth by the confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Schoolemen before cited,<note place="margin">Scot. in <hi>4</hi> diſt. <hi>11</hi> qu. <hi>3.</hi> art. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> the firſt of whom <hi>Scotus</hi> ſayth; If it be enquired, why the Church hath choſen this ſo hard an vnderſtanding of this article about tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, when as the words of the Scripture might be expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſafely according to a more eaſie and true ſenſe in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance: I anſwer that the Catholike Church hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded the Scripture by the ſame Spirit of truth, whereby it was at the firſt deliucred.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elym.</speaker>
               <p>All this will not elude the antiquity of this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. For if tranſubſtantiation were not alwayes held, why was the Maſſe called a ſacrifice, the table an altar, the Miniſter a Prieſt? why hath it alwayes beene ſhewed to the people to be worſhipped, and offered in one kind to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and carryed about with that reuerence, and the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of it kept for the ſame purpoſe in a Pixe to be ready vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all occaſions?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>Wee doe acknowledge that very anciently theſe names of ſacrifice, Altar, and Prieſt were vſurped, but not in your ſenſe. The table of the Lord was called an altar, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the offerings of Chriſtian people comming to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Communion which were brought for the reliefe of the poore, were layd vpon it, according to <hi>Ireuaus,</hi> who ſayth,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> Cap. <hi>32.</hi>
                  </note> that Chriſt by taking bread and wine taught the Diſciples a new oblation of the new Teſtament, the firſt fruits of his creatures. In thoſe Cannons, which are ſayd to be the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,<note place="margin">Can. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> it is or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>yned, that nothing ſhould be offered vpon the alter but eares of corne and frankinſcenſe, and in the 3
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3008:33"/>Councell of <hi>Carthage,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Can. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> that nothing ſhould bee offered but fruits of come and grapes. And hence partly came the name ſacrifice, for almes are a ſacrifice to God: and partly becauſe of the repreſentation of Chriſts ſacrifice made hereby, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is vſuall to call the thing repreſenting by the name of the thing repreſented.<note place="margin">Lomb <hi>1.4.</hi> diſt. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> And ſo <hi>Peter Lomb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd</hi> ſayth, that it is not properly called a ſacrifice, but becauſe it is a memoriall and repreſentation of the true ſacrifice of Chriſt vpon the croſſe. And laſtly, for the ſacrifice of praiſe and thankeſgiuing then offered vnto God. That Chriſtians had not altars properly ſo called is moſt plaine, from <hi>Arnobins,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Arnob. lib. <hi>6.</hi> contra gant. Orig. lib. <hi>8.</hi> cent. Calſ.</note> who ſayth, that the Gentiles accuſed the Chriſtians, becauſe they had no altars: and from <hi>Origen,</hi> who acknowledgeth, that Chriſtians had neither altars, nor images. And therefore as it is called an altar, ſo ſometime it is alſo called a table. See <hi>Auguſt. cont. lit. Petil. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 47. Touching adoration, it was not vſed, till <hi>Honorius</hi> the third, <hi>Anno</hi> 1220, fiue yeares after the Councell of <hi>Laterans</hi> Touching the adminiſtration in one kinde, that was neues vſed,<note place="margin">Def. lib. de offic. py viri.</note> till 1000 yeares after Chriſt, as <hi>Caſſauder</hi> ſheweth, and it was firſt decreed in the Councell of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> vnder Pope <hi>Iobu</hi> the 23, <hi>Anno</hi> 1414 Touching the reſeruation of the remainder, there was a long time no ſuch vſe, for they burnt it in the fire,<note place="margin">Heſych. lib. <hi>2.</hi> in Leuit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> as <hi>Heſych:</hi> teſtifieth; and if ſometime it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, it was by priuate perſons, who caryed it home with them: but was not ſo generally approued; and after more conſideration in Councells condemned, as in the Councell called <hi>Caeſar Auguſtau.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>If any bee preued not to haue conformed the Euchariſt receiued in the Church, let him be anathema.</hi> And in the firſt <hi>Tolletan</hi> Councell:<note place="margin">Cap. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>If they ſhall remaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ill the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, let them not be any longer reſerued, but by the diligence of the Clerciks conſumed.</hi> The name of your Maſſe is very ancient, but then the Maſſe or <hi>miſſa</hi> was a diſmiſſing of the <hi>Catecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meni,</hi> when others remained to receiue, and thus it continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Anno</hi> 600, according to <hi>I ſidor. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Orig. c.</hi> 19. The Maſſe therefore in your Church now is new, and ſo are all your vſages of it, and iuſtly by Chriſtians to be exploded.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I thinke this point hath beene ſo ſeanned, that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3008:33"/>there needs no more to be ſayd, for mine owne part you hour giuen we ſuch light into theſe things, as I neuer had before: for the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient name of the Maſſe and Sacrifice, and Altar, &amp;c. made ſtill ſome ſcruple in my minde, that tranſubſtantiation was a moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient tenent of the Church. But ſeeing I am now fully ſatisfied, proceed to ſome other point.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>The next new thing is the Latine tongue, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Maſſe is offered, and prayers are made, and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are kept. This was not, but where Latine was vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood till the dayes of <hi>Vitalian</hi> Pope, <hi>An.</hi> 666,<note place="margin">Oſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d. Cont. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> in vvhoſe time Latine was firſt vſed in <hi>Conſtantinople:</hi> Neither doth your <hi>Nauclerus</hi> much differ: For hee aſſigneth it to the time of Pope <hi>Agatho, Anno</hi> 675. In the other Countreys, which vnderſtood Latine, as in France, Britaine, and in Africa, it was vſed more anciently: for the Latine tongue was famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar to them for the ſpace of 700 yeares and vpwards, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in one paſſage of the third Councell of <hi>Tours,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 770, wherein it is appointed, that Homilies ſhould bee tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a ruſticke Latine tongue, or <hi>Theotiske,</hi> that they might the better be vnderſtood. So that, if the ſeruice vvas more anciently performed in the Latine tongue, it vvas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they commonly vnderſtood it beſt: but ſince, it not being vnderſtood, it is an abſurd noueltie to vſe it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elym.</speaker>
               <p>It is neceſſarie, that ſeeing Chriſts Church is one, the ſeruice ſhould be vniforme; and for the Scriptures great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to keepe them in an vnknowne tongue, to preuent error.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>It is neceſſarie indeed, as conducing to eſtabliſh the Latine Monarchy; but it were more neceſſary for edification to haue all in a knowne tongue, as anciently it was wont to be, as may be gathered from <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> who ſaith,<note place="margin">Hom. <hi>18.</hi> in <hi>2.</hi> Cor.</note> 
                  <hi>that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayers are made both by the Priest, and the people:</hi> and <hi>Isi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor. When Pſalmes are ſung, they ought to be ſung of all:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Ecst. off. ib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>when Prayer is made, let it be made by all; and when there is reading, let ſilence be made that all may heare.</hi> And for your pretended feare of hereſie, that may be an excuſe: but ſeeing anciently all had the Bible in their owne languages, it cannot but paſſe for a nouclty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be there any more points, the antiquitis whereof you
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3008:34"/>can diſprous, as you haue done theſe?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>Yes: the doctrine of Purgatory and praying for the dead, came in alſo long after the Apoſtles. The firſt that make mention of Purgatory, are <hi>Tertullian</hi> and <hi>Origen,</hi> whoſe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie is not ſo great, becauſe the one was a Montamſt He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticke; and the other was condemned for many errours. In <hi>Auguſtines</hi> time, which was 400 yeares after Chriſt it was ſpoken of but doubtfully.<note place="margin">Tnchit. c. <hi>67.69.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Whether there ſhall bee ſuch a thing or no, it may be enquired, and either be found out, or be kept ſecret from ſome faithfull perſons,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Eſa. l. <hi>28.</hi> c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> And <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaith, that <hi>theſe things are to be left to the iudgement and knowledge of God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Grog. in Iob <hi>13.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> And <hi>Gregory</hi> the firſt, Biſhop of Rome, who was after, <hi>Anno</hi> 600, ſaith, becauſe <hi>we are redcemed, wee haue this benefit, that when we are taken away from the habitation of our fleſh, wee are preſently earied to beauenly rewards.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tertul. de Cor. mil.</note> And the ſame <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> was the firſt, that ſpake of praying for the dead, who alſo conſeſſeth, that <hi>if you require Scripture for it, you ſhall find nonc: but tradition ſhall be pretended as the increaſer; cuſtome the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmer: and faith the obſeruer of it.</hi> Yet it is to bee acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, that euen the moſt approued of the ancient, haue pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the dead, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> for his Mother <hi>Monica,</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe</hi> for <hi>Theodoſius:</hi> but doubtingly becauſe without ground in the Word.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elymas.</speaker>
               <p>Then I hope you will yeeld this to be more an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, then your not praying for the dead, and your vtter denying of Purgatory, as an inuention deriued from the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>hen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>Their praying for the dead was not the ſame vvith yours: but either for the augmentation of their glory, who were in Heauen, as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> hauing ſaid, that <hi>Theodeſius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in the light, and gloried in the company of the Saints: yet he prayeth, <hi>giue perfect reſt to thy ſeruant</hi> Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius;<note place="margin">Confeſ l. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> or to expreſſe their affection, as <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who ſaith of his mother <hi>Monica; I beleeus, that thou haſt done what I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, but accept of the voluntaries of my mouth.</hi> Or if they thought them damned; they prayed for a mitigation of their paines; or holding that they might all bee kept in one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon place, till the day of iudgement, <hi>as La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tantius</hi> ſheweth
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3008:34"/>
                  <hi>de diuin. Draem. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. <hi>Iren. lib.</hi> 5. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y prayed for the haſtening of their Deliuerance. They prayed not for ſoules in Purgatoric; neither did they, which held Purgatory, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that veniall ſinnes were there done away, and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall puniſhments ſatisfied for, till after <hi>Anno</hi> 1000, as your Church now teacheth; and therefore, euen theſe points, as you hold them are new, and vnthought of by antiquity. And ſeeing no ſuch cuſtome is grounded vpon the Word of God, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> hath confeſſed, our denying thus to pray is more Apoſtolicall, and ſo more ancient then either yours or theirs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But thus you will make the Church in the time of theſe holy Fathers to haue beene no true Church, and them no true members, whom we all yet haue in high eſteeme.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>It doth not follow, becauſe they erred in one thing in practice, through too much affection, that they were no Church: for it is not any errour, that ouerturncth the Church; but errours razing the foundation, as hath beene before declared.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elymas.</speaker>
               <p>But theſe holy Fathers vſed the ſame things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſeruice of God that wee doe, as holy Water, and Chriſme, both to the ſicke, and to the baptized, and Exorci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, and Croſſing, and honoured the Saints departed with going to viſit their Reliques, and praying vnto them, and commended a Monaſticall life, and confeſſion to a Prieſt, and workes of penance, wherein the very life of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſiſteth. And therefore if we be no true Church, they were no true Church neither.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>Although there were ſome tincture of theſe ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions in the Church in the dayes of the holy Fathers: yet there was great difference betwixt them and you herein. They vſed the Croſſe, not for any confidence they had in it, but as a ſigne of their profeſſion, as a <hi>Aruobius</hi> teſtifieth, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>We doe neither worſhip, nor wiſh croſſes.</hi> And <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Helena,</hi> who found the Croſſe of Chriſt, faith,<note place="margin">Arnob. l. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Shee found the title, and worſhipped the King, but not the wood.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ambroſ de Obit. Theo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſ.</note> 
                  <hi>For this were a Gentile errour, and a venity of the wicked,</hi> They a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed the ſicke at the beginning of their ſickneſſe in the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3008:35"/>part grieued to eaſe them, as <hi>Gregory Turoneuſis</hi> ſaith. <hi>Hiſt. Franc. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 7. But you to conferre grace at the end of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, when there is no more hope of life. They did not pray to the Saints departed, as able to heare them; but in their ſoliloquies by way of conſabulation through a <hi>Proſopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peia.</hi> For they held, that the Saints departed could not heare them: witneſſe Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who to proue, that they know not what is done, ox ſaid here, bringeth in that place of <hi>Eſai.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">L. de Cura. pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mont. c. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> 63. Abraham <hi>knoweth vs not:</hi> and 2 <hi>King.</hi> 22. <hi>I will gather thee to thy Fathers, that thy eyes may not ſee the ewill to come.</hi> And they did commonly hold then, that all the faithfull departed remained in ſome ſecret place out of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, where they had not the ſight of God; as <hi>Iren. l.</hi> 5. <hi>Iuſt. Martyr. qu.</hi> 60. <hi>&amp;</hi> 76. <hi>Orig. Hom.</hi> 7. <hi>in Leuit. Chryſ. Hom.</hi> 38. <hi>in</hi> 1 <hi>Cor. &amp;c.</hi> And for worſhip they gaue them none, neither <hi>Doulia,</hi> nor <hi>Latria.</hi> For ſo ſaith the ſame <hi>Auguſtine. They are to be honoured for imitation, not bee worſhipped for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. de vera relig. c. <hi>55.</hi>
                  </note> And he vſeth the very word, expreſſing <hi>Doulia. Wee honour the Saints with charitis, not with ſeruice.</hi> Neither did they vſe praying to them in their publique ſeruice. For ſo alſo Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith.<note place="margin">Aug. de Cinit. Dei lib. <hi>22.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> The <hi>Martyrs are named at our ſacrifice, as men of God, that haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uercome the world, but they are not called vpon by the Prieſt that ſacrificeth.</hi> But you pray vnto them in all your Liturgyes, and worſhip them with <hi>Doulia.</hi> And for all other things by you alledged, though they haue been anciently vſed, yet their beginning is not vnknowne vnto vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elym.</speaker>
               <p>But you haue not yet anſwered my argument, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, that our caſe and theirs is all one. For admit, that there were ſome little difference, yet this cannot conclude againſt vs, as no Church, if they were a true Church, ſeeing wee agree together in one kinde of ſeruice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>They agreed not with you in errours againſt the foundation, and therefore were not implicated in the ſame danger, as euen in this about the Saints departed, where the chiefe danger lyeth, <hi>viz.</hi> in worſhipping them, and truſting to them, as to Mediators, that ſhall preuaile, and that haue power to helpe. But you ſhall not thus put me from the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3008:35"/>firſt thing propounded: <hi>viz.</hi> to ſhew the beginning of theſe ſuperſtitions. Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> firſt inſtituted Holy Water, <hi>Anno</hi> 115. <hi>Sabel. Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>Concil.</hi> Pope <hi>Hig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Chry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ne in Baptiſme, <hi>Anno</hi> 141. <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 4 <hi>c.</hi> 10. An Exorcift was firſt ordained by Pope <hi>Caius, Anno</hi> 283. <hi>Sabel.</hi> The ſigne of the Croſſe was not vſed, but for ſignification 300 yeares; or if for bleſſing, with inuocation vpon him that was crucified, the truſt not being in it, but in Chriſt crucified. A materiall Croſſe or Crucifixe, was not ſet vp till 400 yeares after Chriſt: neither was it appointed, till <hi>Anno</hi> 710, when the <hi>Trullan</hi> Councell ordained,<note place="margin">Cap. <hi>82.</hi> Policbron l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi> Can. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> that Chriſt ſhould bee pictured hanging vpon the Croſſe. The firſt Croſſe erected in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, was <hi>Anno</hi> 635, in the time of King <hi>Oſwald.</hi> In the fift <hi>Carth.</hi> Councell, <hi>Anno</hi> 409. the worſhipping of Saints Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, is declared to be heatheniſh: and ſupplication vvas made to the Emperour, that Reliques ſhould be aboliſhed, In a Councell at <hi>Laodu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ea, Anno</hi> 368, the worſhipping of Angels is condemned, as horrible idolatry. <hi>Petrus Gnapheus</hi> is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed to bee the firſt, that brought inuocation vpon the Saints into the publique ſeruice, <hi>Anno</hi> 500:<note place="margin">Niceph. l. <hi>15</hi> c. <hi>28.</hi>
                  </note> and at euery turne the mention of the Mother of our Lord. And about <hi>Anno</hi> 600, Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the firſt appointed your Liturgy with prayers to all the Saints, as now it is. <hi>Anthony</hi> was the firſt that renouncing the world, led a ſolitary life in the Wilderneſſe, becauſe of the hot perſecutions of the Church, <hi>Anno</hi> 300. For ſo <hi>Friſing</hi> ſaith;<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>There were in theſe dayes fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Princes of Cbriſts Kingdome,</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Antony <hi>the firſt Eremites.</hi> And <hi>Baſilius</hi> firſt built Monaſteries:<note place="margin">Baſil. Epiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>63.</hi>
                  </note> for hee ſaith that the <hi>Neoceſareaus</hi> obiected vnto him the newneſſe of a Monaſticall life. <hi>Euſtatius</hi> an Hereticke extolled a Monaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call life, and condemned mariage, holding it neceſſary to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, to forſake all and to turne Monke. Againſt him a Councell was aſſembled at <hi>Gangra, Anno</hi> 324, and his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions were condemned, where they profeſſed, that they ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured true Virginity, and withall the chaſte bond of mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, &amp;c. Auticular confeſſion to a Prieſt began not, till <hi>An.</hi> 800. It was firſt appointed <hi>in Concil. Cabiloneuſi</hi> 2. c. 32. and <hi>coneil. Mogunt.</hi> in the time of <hi>Gregory</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 26. Before if it
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3008:36"/>were vſed, yet it was not inioyned, yea, warning was giuen againſt it.<note place="margin">Chryſ. hom. <hi>4.</hi> de Laz.</note> 
                  <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith; <hi>Take heed that thou tell not thy ſinnes to man, leſt bee vpbraid thee; but ſhew thy wounds to the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Scal paradiſi Grad.</note> 
                  <hi>that hath a care of thee, that is gentle, that is the Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi> And Iohannes Climacus, <hi>An.</hi> 580. <hi>Before all things, let vs confeſſe our ſinnes onely to the Lord our iudge, and bee ready at his command to confeſſe them to all men.</hi> And with confeſſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan workes of penance. For before, <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeaking, how a man might attaine peace with God, ſaith, Hee <hi>hath not commanded thee to paſſe ouer the Mountaines,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſ. in Math. Hom. <hi>55.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>to ſayle ouer the Seas, to digge ſo much ground, to remaine faſting, or to put on ſackcloth; but to giue of that which thou haſt vnto the poore.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But ſeeing you acknowledge moſt of theſe things to be very ancient, and the Fathers which ſubſcribed vnto them with the Church in their dayes, to be the true Church of God: Why haue you vtterly aboliſhed all theſe things? Had it not been bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to haue reſtored them onely to that ſtate wherein they were in the time of the Fathers, cutting off the acceſſions that haue ſince been made?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>No, by no meanes, for it would not haue beene ſo ſafe to hold theſe cuſtomes after their manner, ſeeing they haue ſince proued rootes of moſt peſtilent weeds, leſt in time, there ſhould bee danger of the ſame euils comming on againe. Euen as it is no wiſedome in taking away B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars and Thornes off a ground, to preſerue the rootes ſtill. For from their praying for the dead to expreſſe their affection, if happily they might increaſe their ioyes, or mitigate their paines, ſprung an opinion of a third place, wherein the ſoules of the faithfull are tormented, but may bee holpen out by praying for them. From vſing a croſſe in the aire for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of their Chriſtian profeſſion, ſprung confidence, and adoration of the Croſſe. From mentioning the Saints departed ouer their altars, praiſing God for them, ſprung praying vnto them. From annoiling to heale ſickneſſe of the body, ſprung annoiling to conferre grace to the ſoule. From a Monaſticall life taken vp for neceſſity, ſprung vp an opinion of the neceſſity of a Monkiſh life in all, that would be perfect, and of the merit hereof.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:3008:36"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>You haue not yet ſhewed the firſt broaching of that doctrine touching freewill, inſtification by workes in part, vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of faith, of perfection, the merit of workes, and of workes of ſupererrogation: nor of Chriſts ſatisfaction onely for eternall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, which you ſhewed did chiefely pull downe the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. I pray you therefore now ſhew the beginning of theſe points alſo.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>This whole brood was hatched almoſt at one time, <hi>viz.</hi> of the Schoolemen about <hi>Anno</hi> 1200, or of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Trent, Anno</hi> 1500. That man hath freewill to deſire to trune vnto God, as one wounded and halfe dead hath to be ſuccoured, was vtterly reiected by the Fathers, eſpecially af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that occaſion was giuen by <hi>Pelagius</hi> an Hercticke, to looke more narrowly into the truth hereabout. Before, they ſpeake ſomewhat vncertainly;<note place="margin">De Sp. &amp; lib. c. <hi>3.</hi> de dogmat. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae c. <hi>27.</hi> Cont. Epiſt. <hi>2.</hi> Pelag. l. <hi>3</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> but then <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith; <hi>Freewill anatleth to nothing but to ſinne.</hi> And againe, <hi>A holy thought, a good purpoſe, a godly counſell, and euery motion of a good wil is from God.</hi> And againe, <hi>freewill anaileth to nothing but to ſinne.</hi> And with him conſenteth <hi>Ierome</hi> againſt <hi>Pelagius:</hi> and <hi>Proſper,</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> who ſaith, that wicked men are altogether dead. Yea, to the dayes of <hi>Bernard</hi> the ſame was held. For he ſaith, <hi>We haue power to will,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Barn. de gra &amp; lib. arbuitrio.</note> 
                  <hi>but neither good nor euill: to will good is a profect, to will euill is a defect. O—r freewill maketh vs willing, but grace well willing.</hi> And nothing is more frequent amongſt the Fathers, then to teach, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer proccedeth from a naturall man is ſinne.<note place="margin">Ieron. in Gal c. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> Heare <hi>Ierome</hi> for all, who ſaith, <hi>without Chriſt all vertue is vice.</hi> This point then is not yet foure hundred yeares old.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elymas.</speaker>
               <p>Nothing was more frequent in the mouths of the Fathers before <hi>Pelagius,</hi> then freewill.<note place="margin">Apol. 1. Lib <hi>4</hi> c. <hi>71.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> ſaith, that <hi>there were nothing in men worthy of praiſe, if they had not equall power to turne themſelues either way. Ireneus</hi> ſaith; Man <hi>hath power to chooſe, euen as the Augels.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their impugning of freewill afterwards was to bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to the heat of their oppoſition made to <hi>Pelagius,</hi> who taug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that men had power to turne to God, and to keepe his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mmandements out of the libertie of their free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:3008:37"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>That which you alleage touching their oppugning <hi>Pelagius,</hi> may much more truely bee applyed about their ſayings, wherein they ſeeme to be for the freedome of mans will: for they had to doe with the <hi>Marcionitel,</hi> and <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichces,</hi> who held a neceſſity of all things wherby men were caried either to good or euill; and hence it came to paſſe, that they vttered ſuch ſayings as theſe: but when they ſaw the danger of the Hereſie touching free will enſuing, they laboured by ſpeaking againſt it to quite themſelues from the leaſt aſperſion this way.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And truely this is moſt likely: for the proper time for a man to expreſſe what he holdeth, is then, when diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is moued about it, whereas be ſpeaketh not ſo warily at other times, when be feareth not that any hold will bee taken vpon his ſayings againſt the truth. And I am the rather perſwaded, that they were againſt all liberty of the will vnto good, becauſe they ſo conſentingly taught, that euery thing proceeding from a naturall man before his conuerſion is ſinne.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>Touching iuſtification by workes, or by inherent righteouſneſſe, and not onely by the righteouſneſſe. of Chriſt imputed by faith, none euer taught it, till <hi>An.</hi> 1500. For Chriſts righteouſneſſe onely hath euer heene reſted vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the Fathers:<note place="margin">Ieron in <hi>2</hi> Cor. <hi>5.</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Cor. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaith, <hi>Chriſt hath ſo receued the name of ſinne, as we are made the righteouſneſſe of God in him, not ours, nor in vs. Ambroſe</hi> ſayth, <hi>This is appointed of God, that he which beloeueth in Chriſt ſhould be ſaued without workes, hauing his ſinnes freely forgiuen through faith onely.</hi> And <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">In Rom. <hi>3.</hi> Hom <hi>7.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>190.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>So ſoone as a man beleeueth, he is iuſtified. Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>Another mans righteouſneſſe is aſſigned vnto man, becauſe he wanted his owne, the ſatisfaction of one is imputed to vs all.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elym.</speaker>
               <p>But there is a double iuſtification: the firſt, which is onely by faith, and hereby a man paſſeth from the ſtate of ſin into the eſtate of grace: and the ſecond, which is by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mherent righteouſneſſe, whereby a man of iuſt becommeth more iuſt and worthy of heauen. And of the firſt of theſe onely the Fathers ſpake, not of the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>They could not well ſpeake of that, ſeeing it was vnknowne in their dayes, and long ſince inuented. And
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3008:37"/>touching the merit of the beſt mans righteouſneſſe. <hi>Bernard</hi> doth vtterly deny it, ſaying, <hi>The merits of men are not ſuch,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bernard Ser. <hi>1.</hi> de An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n.</note> 
                  <hi>as that for them eternall life ſhould be due of right; or ſo as that God ſhould be vniuſt, if he did not therefore beſtow eternall life: for to ſay nothing, that allour merits are Gods gifts, and ſo man is for them a debter vnto God, not God vnto man; what are all me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to ſo great glory?</hi> Wherefore if meriting bee ſpoken of by the Fathers, they meant nothing elſe but to preuaile or obtaine, or elſe they called good works merits, to ſet forth their dignity in reſpect of the diuine acceptance, that men might be incouraged hereunto.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elym.</speaker>
               <p>You doe altogether peruert their meaning: for they taught good workes in the regenerate to be properly meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, ſeeing perfect righteouſnes according to the law is worthy of heauen, and ſuch righteouſneſſe they taught, that men through the grace of God inabling them, did attaine vnto in this life, yea and that they could doe and did more then the law required, and ſo merited for others alſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>You doe moſt impudently wrong the Fathers: for none till aboue 1000 yeares after Chriſt, taught perfection of degrees in this life, but onely perfection through Chriſt, and a comparatiue perfection, ſome exceeding others; but altogether againſt it. Saint. <hi>Angustine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Charity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>29.</hi> ad Hieron.</note> 
                  <hi>that cannot be increaſed is in no man bere, and that which may bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed is in fault, becauſe it is leſſe, then it ought to be, by reaſon of which fault there is no man iuſt and ſinneth not, by reaſon of which fault no liuing man ſhall bee iuſtified in the ſight of God.</hi> And <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaith, to affirme that any man liueth ſo, as that he is without ſinne, is <hi>to take man out of man, and to affirme that a man in the body is without the body,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ierom contra Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lag. Epiſt.</note> 
                  <hi>and rather to wiſh then to teach.</hi> And if they held, that no man can perfectly keepe the Law, then it is certaine, that they taught not, that men could both doe all that the Law requireth, and more alſo. If then they haue ſpoken any thing, wherein they may ſeeme to be for ſupererogation, it is to be vnderſtood either of outward things, or of ſome ſpeciall commendable thing, which is not commonly commanded to all, but commended to ſome. And ſo their doing more then is required was onely with
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3008:38"/>reference vnto others; who did not likewiſe as not hauing that particular gift,<note place="margin">Hom. <hi>3.</hi> in <hi>1.</hi> Cor.</note> or in exterials, wherein <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſaith, <hi>euen the Philoſophers exceeded the Commandement of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I like this your interpretation of the Fathers ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, and am hereby perſwaded, that both perfect keeping of the Law and workes of ſupererrogation are nouelties. Proced there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to vncertainty of faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>This vncertainty was not determined, not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of faith condemned, before the Councell of <hi>Trent Anno</hi> 1500. The Fathers are moſt plaine for aſſurance by faith.<note place="margin">Aug. Tract <hi>75.</hi> in Johan.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſt:</hi> ſaith, Chriſt is now in vs, and we in him, <hi>but we beleeue this now, then wee ſhall know it, although we know it now alſo through beleeuing, but then we ſhall know it by bebolding it.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Regiſt. lib. <hi>6.187.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith; <hi>The ſoule that thirſteth after God is firſt pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with feare, then with loue, but when ſeare hath beene conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with long anxiety of ſorrow, a certaine ſecurity of preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of pardon doth ariſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hom. <hi>14.</hi> in Rom. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> And <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſayth: <hi>The ſupreme Eſſence, which doth alſo beſtow what it promiſeth, teſtifying vnto vs, who can any more doubt of this dignity hereafter?</hi> And <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> exhorteth to beleeue without doubting,<note place="margin">Bern in Cant. Serm. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Whatſoeuer ſoule of you feeleth at any time in the ſecret of his conſcience the Spirit of the Sonne crying</hi> Abba <hi>Father, let it preſume that it is beloued with afatherly affection, and beleeue, doubting nothing.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elym.</speaker>
               <p>They meant nothing elſe, but certainty on Gods part, but becauſe man is mutable, and all promiſer runne vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on condition of his perſeuerance, they haue plainely taught elſewhere, that none can be certaine by faith. Heare <hi>Auguſt.</hi> for all, who ſayth. <hi>Who of all the multitude of beleeuers can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume that he is in the number of beleeuers as long as he is in this mortality.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>They ſpake in this manner to preuent carnall ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which followeth vpon preſumption, but they neuer impugned, but incouraged to aſſurance by faith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>There remaineth now onely one point, wherein I deſire to heare you speake,</hi> viz. <hi>that of ſatis faction.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>And this is none of their leaſt errors, that Chriſt ſatisfied onely for eternall puniſhments, but for temporall due vnto vs for ſinne we our ſelues are to ſatisfie: for as it is a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3008:38"/>plaine derogation fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dignity of his paſſions. Touching this therefore I ſay, as of the former points it was not taught anciently, but the plaine contary: <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Tertul. de Baptiſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Guiltineſſe being taken away, the puniſhment is alſo taken away;</hi> and that he may not ſeeme to ſpeake of eternall puniſhments onely, hee nameth death, according as it was threatned,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note> 
                  <hi>In the day that thou cateſt of it, thou ſhalt dye the death,</hi> which death here com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth all puniſhments. And Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cbit. c. <hi>70.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt by taking vpon him the puniſhment, and not the fault, hath done away both fault and puniſhment:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. de verb. Dom. Scr. <hi>37.</hi>
                  </note> and elſewhere more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly; <hi>Chriſt had two good things, righteouſneſſe, and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, wee two euill things, ſinne and wortality, the one hee tooke vpon him, the other he did not, and by taking vpon him the one, he freed vs from both.</hi> As for ſatisfaction required of vs, it is not, as he ſheweth, for puniſhment, but to ſhew our repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance by our outward actions. So that according to <hi>Auguſt.</hi> wee are deliuered from mortality as a puniſhment, and not only from hell fire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elym.</speaker>
               <p>Howſoeuer you ſeeme to make theſe learned Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to ſpeake, it is plaine, that they meant onely eternall puniſhments, borne by Chriſt for vs. And therefore they doe vſually ſpeake of works of penance and almes, as hauing force to purge and waſh away ſinne. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Hom. <hi>1.</hi> in Gen.</note> 
                  <hi>The common Lord of vs all, deſirous to haue all our ſinnes waſhed away, hath inuented this cure, which is made by faſting.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. de promiſ &amp; prad. part. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> Hom. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> And <hi>Proſper</hi> ſaith, <hi>Almes cleanſe the whole man.</hi> And <hi>Ceſarius</hi> ſayth, <hi>that a man who by ſinning hath loſt himſelfe, doth agains redeeme him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by his ſatisfaction.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>Where is there a word in all theſe touching ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for temporall puniſhments? It may rather bee infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, if theſe ſpeeches be ſtrictly taken, that wee are able to doe ſomething to deliuer our ſelues from ſinne, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of guilt and puniſhment temporall &amp; eternall. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt needs bee yeelded, that theſe things were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken improperly, that being aſcribed to the inſtrument or meanes, which is proper vnto Chriſt. Satisfaction there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as it is now taught in your Church, is rather to bee referred to the <hi>Lateran</hi> Councell, <hi>Anno</hi> 1215, wherein
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3008:39"/>the ſacrament of penance was eſtabliſhed, an appendix whereof is ſatisfaction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elym.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe you haue ſpoken of the ſacrament of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance firſt appointed in the <hi>Lateran</hi> Councell, I will lay hold vpon the occaſion to put you to proue the nouelty of the ſeuen ſacraments: for if ſeuen haue beene anciently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, this is not ſo new, as you would make the world beleeue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>I am very willing to follow you herein, and let the iſſue reſt vpon my prouing your ſeuen Sacraments to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelties. I ſay then, that this number was not knowne, nor acknowledged by antiquity, but was firſt taught by <hi>Peter Lombard</hi> and the Schoole-men following him, aboue 1000 yeares after Chriſt.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 118.</note> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth, <hi>the Sacraments of the New Teſtament are moſt few in number. Iſidorus</hi> An. 600 ſayth,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>6</hi> Originum c. <hi>19.</hi> Paſc. de Caena.</note> 
                  <hi>The Sacraments are Baptiſme and Chriſme, and the body and blood of Chriſt.</hi> And <hi>Paſcaſius Anno</hi> 900; ſayth likewiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elym.</speaker>
               <p>They ſay, theſe two are the chiefe indeed, but they exclude not the reſt. <hi>Hugo de Sancto <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictore</hi> teacheth ſeuen ſacraments, and of them he ſaith ſome are the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall, wherein ſaluation ſtandeth,<note place="margin">Lib. de ſacram. <hi>7.</hi> part. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> Baptiſme and the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lord; the reſt though they bee not ſo neceſſary, yet they profit vnto ſanctification. And I could eaſily ſhew, that the ancienteſt Fathers haue called euery of theſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>I grant you without ſhewing, that they called them ſacraments, and ſo they called any holy ſigne, according to <hi>Auguſtines</hi> definition;<note place="margin">Auguſt. Epiſt. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Euery holy ſigue is a Sacrament.</hi> But that there are any more, then two, properly ſo called, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer taught, and euen your <hi>Hugo,</hi> who acknowledgeth 7, can be no ground for your 7, for he reckoneth not penance for one, but the water of aſperſion. And the very Schoolemen deny the reſt to be ſacraments,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 4.26.</note> properly ſo called. <hi>P. Lombard</hi> denyeth Matrimony to be a Sacrament properly and vniuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally with the other ſacraments, and <hi>Durand</hi> likewiſe vpon that place.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>diſt.</hi> 24.</note> The ſame <hi>Lombard</hi> denyeth ordination to bee properly a ſacrament, and <hi>Alexander de Hales,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> vpon that place, &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:3008:39"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>This your diſpute about the Sacraments hath brought to my mind another point yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>toucht about the holy Scriptures and Traditions. Can you ſhew, that it is a noueliy is hold, that to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Canonical Scriptures, Apocryphall bookes are to be receiued, and vnwritten traditions, as a rule of our ſaith, or hath it euer beene held thus?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>It is a nouelty to hold, that the Scriptures doe not containe in them all things neceſſary to ſaluation, and that Apocryphall bookes are to be receiued as Canonicall, and that traditious are neceſſary to ſaluation. For the Fathers ſought to hold all men onely to the Scriptures:<note place="margin">Hom. <hi>1.</hi> in Pſal. <hi>95.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, <hi>If any thing bee ſpoken without Scripture, the thought of the bearers limpeth, ſometimes yeelding, and ſometime doubting.</hi> And againe, <hi>If ye hears any ſaying, I haue the holy Spirit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Serm. de S. Sp.</note> 
                  <hi>but not ſpeaking out of the Goſpell, bee ſpeaketh of himſelfe, and the holy Spirit is not in him.</hi> So <hi>Baſil, reg. Mor.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 28. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 80. And touching Apocryphall books, <hi>Cyril. Hieruſalym,</hi> ſayth; <hi>Haus nothing to doe with Apocryphall bookes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Catee. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>but read the canonicall which are conſidently read in the Church. The Apoſtles and firſt Biſhops were much wiſer and more religious then thou, who deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered the ſcriptures vnto vs. Doe not thou therefore, ſeeing thou art a child of the Church, ges beyond their bounds.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Athen in Synop.</note> 
                  <hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſayth, <hi>There are</hi> 22 <hi>bookes of the old Teſtament Canonicall, but there are other bookes which are not Canonicall, which are onely read of the</hi> Catecumeni, <hi>as the booke of</hi> Wiſdome, Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, &amp;c. <hi>Ierom</hi> calleth the Hiſtory of <hi>Suſamus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prafat. in Den.</note> of <hi>Bel and the Dragon</hi> fables, and ſaith the ſame was the opinion of <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius, Apollinarius, Methodius, &amp;c. Baruch</hi> was not receiued as Canonicall till the Councell of <hi>Florence, Anno</hi> 1439. And touching vnwritten traditions, they receiued none of old, but either ſuch as were conſonant to the holy Scriptures, which were written in ſenſe, though not in word, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> of which was the baptiſme of Infants and not to rebaptize:<note place="margin">De Gen, ad lit. lib. <hi>10</hi> c. <hi>23.</hi> Tertul de Coron. c. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> or cuſtomes in indifferent things ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>Doſt thou not thinke, that it is lawfull for euery faithfull Church to conceiue and conſtituent that which agreeth to God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to diſeiplione, and profireth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation?</hi> And theſe by the preſtice of your owne Church
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:3008:40"/>may be left off again. For the thrice dipping in Baptiſin, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in time of prayer vpon the Lords day, taſting of milke and honcy in Baptiſme, &amp;c. anciently receiued, are now abrogated, and not held to bind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elym.</speaker>
               <p>I could reioyne with you about this argument, and bring many paſſages of the Fathers ſhewing their high e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme of traditions: but leſt theſe diſputes ſhould proue tedious to this noble perſon, and that he may not, being faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinated with that which you haue ſaid, incline to your colourable Hereſies, I ſay that all, which you haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to diſgrace the Catholike Religion as nouell, are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but cauils. For if our Religion be new, and ſo faire degenerated, as that the foundation is hereby ouerthrowne, there was no Religion, and ſo no true Church of God in the world for many hundred yeares, ſeeing by your owne confeſſion, the Church which was aboue 1000 or 1300 yeares agoe, had many cuſtomes, and held many things which you doe not at this day. And with what face then can you alledge them, as being on your ſide ſo commonly as you doe, as though your Church were all one with theirs, when as it is plaine to any that will vnderſtand, that they are our Fathers, and not yours; and ſuch as ſuffered death, our Martyrs, ſealing vp with their blood the Romane Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thohke Religion, and not your new deuiſed way of ſeruing God without croſſing, Chryſme, Holy water, Prayers for the dead, deuotion to the Saints, &amp;c. and full of carnall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, in all things pleaſing to the fleſh, as mariages of Prieſts, and worldly liuing of all, without any renouncing of ſecular affaires for the ſeruice of God, and repenting on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with a little griefe, no workes of penance being after required, with many other points of licentiouſneſſe. If any held with this Religion in all theſe points, tell who they were, when and where they liued, if you can, till within theſe hundred yeares, and that is as late as the neweſt of our points, to grant you your owne ſaying.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>Neuer were any ſo iuſtly to bee taxed for cauil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, as you: for what can it elſe bee, when all your points, in that manner you hold them, haue beene plainly ſhewed
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:3008:40"/>to bee new, to fly to this generall reaſon for euaſion? The Church in the time of theſe ancients, was the ſame with ours in all matters of faith, as I haue fully declared, neither can a few ceremonies ſince, more corrupted, and therefore by vs aboliſhed, eſtrange our Church from theirs, no more then the breaking downe of the braſen Serpent, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God without it in <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> dayes, eſtranged the Church then from the Church in the time of <hi>Moſes.</hi> As for the holy Martyrs, it is a moſt vaine bragge that they ſealed your Religion with their blood, which was not then in queſtion. It was rather our Religion, that they ſealed, ſeeing they commonly ſuffered for ſuch zeale to Chriſt, as that together with him they would not worſhip Idols, as we alſo refuſe to doe. For holding the ſame points with vs in euery particular, it is not neceſſary to ſhew any that did, it is ſufficient to proue our Religion true, and Apoſtolicall, to haue ſhewed the riſing vp of all thoſe rites, that we ahue done away, to haue beene long after the Apoſtles dayes. And for carnall liberty, whereby you ſeeke to diſgrace the truth, herein you blaſpheme the very liberty of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, after the manner of the malicious Phariſees, who cryed out vpon Chriſt; <hi>Behold a glution, and drinker of wine, a friend of Publicans and ſinners.</hi> When hee did no more then hee might in taking liberty herein. For euen ſo wee maintaine liberty of mariage to all men, and reiect your ſuperſtitious auſterities; becauſe mariage is honourable amongſt all men, and wee would not through a multitude of obſeruances make Chriſts eaſie yoake and light burden, heauy,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.4.</note> like to that vnder the Law, of which Saint <hi>Peter</hi> complaineth that it was ſuch, <hi>that neither we, nor our Fathers were able to beare.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 15.10.</note> And if experience may be heard, this your taking vpon you to be ſtricter then God, ſhall bee abundantly conuinced to opon a farre wider gap to licentiouſneſſe, ſeeing all he world ringeth of the carnality, vncleanneſſe, and diſſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of your very votaries and Prieſts, and of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe aboue all. And it is obſerued, that your very Confeſſions and appointments of penance is turned into a fountaine of liberty, ſeeing more rioes and diſorders are againſt the time
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:3008:41"/>of ſhrift in <hi>Italy</hi> comitted, then all the yeare before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But can you not ſhow any that were of your reformed Religion for ſubſtance and matter of faith from the time of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers, till</hi> Luther. <hi>That was a very long diſtance of time of about</hi> 1000 <hi>yeares. Doe you hold that God was without a true viſible Church all this time?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>God was neuer without a true Church, neither was ſhe hid long at any time: For till the Pope was made an Idoll, and idolatry with Images, and with the Maſſe tooke place in the Church, and the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was made ioynt mediator with Chriſt, it was a true Church, which was till about <hi>Anno</hi> 700. And when the Latine Church was by theſe abhominations corrupted, the Greek Church ſtill continued more ſound: for they withſtood the Popes ſupremacy, oppoſed images, held no tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; neither ſubſcribed to the points maintained by the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts, till the Councell of <hi>Florence, Anno</hi> 1439, at what time I haue alſo ſhewed, how much this ſubſcription was miſ-liked by the body of that Church. So that if no where elſe, yet in <hi>Grecia</hi> the true Church was to be found, till then. But there wanted not oppugners of Images, and of the Popes ſupremacy in other places at the ſame times. The Councell of <hi>Franckford</hi> was famous for determining againſt Images, as I haue alſo declared. Betweene 700 and <hi>Anno</hi> 800 <hi>Albertus Gallus</hi> a French Biſhop oppoſed himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Pope in his Legate <hi>Boniface,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hiſt. Magd. Cent. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> and with him one <hi>Clemens</hi> a presbyter, and <hi>Saemſon,</hi> who were therefore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated by the Pope, and impriſoned. And about the ſame time <hi>Iohan Mailroſius</hi> and <hi>Claudius Clemens</hi> ſent from <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp; firſt Profeſſors of learning in the Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Paris,</hi> denyed to ſubſcribe to the Romiſh ſuperſtitions. Betweene 800 and 900 <hi>Claudius Taurinenſis</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin</hi> in <hi>Piemont,</hi> denyed the Pope, to bee an Apoſtolike Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, for he is not, ſayd he, an Apoſtolike Biſhop, that ſitteth in the Apoſtolike chaire, but that fulfilleth an Apoſtolike office.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Whights</hi> way to the Church. p. <hi>386.</hi>
                  </note> He caſt images out of the Church, and impugned the worſhipping of the croſſe. About that time were <hi>Ioh. Scotus</hi> alſo and <hi>Bertram</hi> that denyed the reall preſence, <hi>Anno</hi> 847.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:3008:41"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thergandus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Treniris</hi> inueighed againſt Pope <hi>Nicolas,</hi> calling him Antichriſt,<note place="margin">Auentin: Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nold. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> for which he was excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, and afterwards ſtaine. Betweene <hi>An.</hi> 900 and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>000, <hi>Otho</hi> impugned the ſupremacy,<note place="margin">Uhite ibid.</note> and <hi>Arnulphus</hi> called the Pope Antichriſt. Betweene <hi>An.</hi> 1000 and 1100, <hi>Berengarius</hi> impugned the reall preſence, of whom I haue already ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. About that time <hi>Leaskerius</hi> an Archbiſhop in France was of the ſame opinion. Berweene <hi>An.</hi> 1100, and 1200. A certaine Biſhop of Florence preached,<note place="margin">Hiſt. Magd. Cent. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> that Antichriſt vvas come, in the time of <hi>Paſcalis</hi> the ſecond. Alſo one <hi>Francis</hi> an Abbor, and <hi>Petrus do Beuis</hi> a Prieſt, impugned the reall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, with many other Popiſh points: and <hi>Bernard</hi> is famous for many points againſt Popery. Betweene <hi>Anno</hi> 1200,<note place="margin">Hiſt Magd. Cent. <hi>13.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> and 1300, <hi>Gulielm. de Sancto amers,</hi> was baniſhed for an heretike and had his bookes burnt; and <hi>Robert Groſted</hi> Biſhop of Lincolne, greatly oppoſed the Pope. Between <hi>An.</hi> 1300 and 1400, was <hi>Iohn Wickliffe</hi> profeſſor of diuinitie in Oxford, who oppoſed the Pope in ſundry points.<note place="margin">Hiſt. Magd. Cent. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> And out of <hi>Greece</hi> came diuers by reaſon of the Turkiſh tyranny, amongſt whom <hi>Marſilius Patauinus</hi> was of moſt note: he, maintained that the Pope had no power ouer other Biſhops, much leſſe ouer Kings. <hi>Armachanus</hi> an Archb. in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Iohannes de Rupeſeiſſa</hi> were of the ſame opinion alſo. And after this <hi>Iohn Huſſe,</hi> and <hi>Ierome</hi> of <hi>Prague,</hi> with almoſt all the country of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> were famous for ſtanding for the truth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But theſe were but a few in an age, neither could they make a Church: how hapned it, that there were no more till.</hi> Wickliffes <hi>time?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>Where Biſhops and learned teachers haue been ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp to ſtand for the truth, there is no doubt, but as lights of the world they did inlighten many more, though they be to vs vnknowne. Neither was the myſterie of iniquity growne to that height till about <hi>Wickliffes</hi> time, and the dayes of the ſucceeding Worthies, ſo that the Romane reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion was not altogether ſo dangerous: but now they being almoſt quite gone from Chriſt, their ſuperſtitious deuotion increaſing towards the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and the reſt of the Saints, ſatisfying for a mans owne ſins in part, being taught,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:3008:42"/>and the merit of workes, and freedome of will ſet vp, and the aſſurance of faith condemned, and ſuch horrible idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try with the Maſſe more then euer committed, they which had the Spirit of God in any meaſure within them could no longer forbeare, but in great companies vtterly ſeparate from the Church of Rome, leſt whilſt they would bee wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of Chriſt, they ſhould become limmes of Antichriſt, to the deſtruction of their ſoules.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elymas.</speaker>
               <p>Nay rather are ye now become limmes of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, by following <hi>Martin Luther</hi> a Monke, that brake his Vow, and maried a Nunne, &amp; was of a notorious wicked life, and had conſultation with the Deuill, and ſo went to the Deuill at the laſt: and by following King <hi>Henry</hi> 8, a man ſo ſenſuall and tyranicall; for theſe and ſuch like were your leaders to this Schiſme, and not any good Spirit, as yee pretend.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>In ſeeking to wound the truth through the ſides of theſe men, you doe but according to your accuſtomed man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, it being one of the Pillars of your Religion, to lay ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous imputations vpon your Aduerſaries, as a late Writer of ours hath notably ſhewed.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Willet</hi> Tetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtul. Papiſmi.</note> But as for <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> it is well knowne, that he was a man of great zeale for the truth, and ſucceeded accordingly; your Pope and all your power not being able to lay violent hands vpon him, but that hee was preſerued to dye in peace. If there were any thing tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in him, in what holy man hath there not beene like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is no preiudice to the truth, which hee ſtood for: no more, then Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> forepaſſed perſecuting and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming was to the Goſpel. And for King <hi>Henry</hi> 8, God can vſe any inſtrument to beat down the pride of ſuch an enemy as the Pope, as be vſed <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> to chaſtice idolatrous <hi>Iudah,</hi> and the Syrian Preſidents, and Romane Emperours, to deſtroy Chriſts enemies, and to abrogate the legall ſeruice by burning vp the Temple, and yet this made nothing the more for the credit of the Iewes Religion, or diſcredit of the Chriſtian thus aduanced. But becauſe you haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen mee ſo iuſt occaſion, I ſay that if the wickedneſſe and miſcrable ends of chiefe erectors of any Religion,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:3008:42"/>be an argument of a bad religion, as vndoubtedly it is, the Religion of the Church of Rome is abundantly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced to bee ſuch; ſeeing ſo many Poper haue beene ſo notoriouſly wicked, and periſhed ſo miſerably, and ſuch ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant iudgements haue beene executed vpon others, that hath holpen to aduance it. <hi>Gregory</hi> the third, who drew vp the Popedome to ſuch a high pin, was a moſt wicked man: for when <hi>Phocas,</hi> who had murthered <hi>Mauricius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Platina.</note> and was therefore greatly taxed by the Patriarke of Conſtantinople, for which hee was much offended with him, hee ſent his image to Rome, and <hi>Gregory</hi> receiued it honourably, and flattereth with this parricide, but inioyed not long the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of vniuerſall Biſhop thus attained, for he dyed within nine moneths after. And <hi>Phocas</hi> the founder of the primacy proued ſoone after a ſlothfull beaſt,<note place="margin">Pompon. Latus Paul. Diacon.</note> cruelly murthering ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Nobles, rauiſhing many Matrons and Virgins, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in dayly drunkenneſſe, and acocrdingly was rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. For hee was taken by <hi>Priſcus,</hi> and <hi>Heracleon,</hi> and his hands being faſt cut off, then his priuy member, he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed, and his body burnt in a brazen Bull,<note place="margin">R. Barus ſupplem. Chron. Nancl.</note> and all his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity deſtroyed with him. <hi>Silueſter</hi> the ſecond was a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurer, and was ſlaine by the Deuil,<note place="margin">Iob. Marius.</note> when he was ſaying Maſſe in the Chappell of the Croſſe of Ieruſalem. <hi>Iohn</hi> the 13 committed Inceſt with two of his Sifters, and was ſlaine at the laſt in the act of Adultery. <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeuenth put out the eyes of <hi>Iohn</hi> the 15, and killed him with famine in the Caſtle of Saint <hi>Angelo,</hi> that he might reigne in his ſtead; and hauing laboured mightily to aduance the papall Sea, he was ſhortly cut off by a ſudden death, and his body was drawne by the feet through the ſtreets,<note place="margin">Faſcic. Temp. Otho <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> and pierced with ſpeares by the Romanes. Whereupon the Hiſtory called <hi>Foſciculus tempor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> noreth, that <hi>the Biſhops of Rome were now adayes ſlaine, as in the Primitiue Church, but were not made Martyrs as they, there was the like death, but not the like cauſe: thy ſuffered, as wailde lambes following the Lambr Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plat. vit. pontif.</note> 
                  <hi>theſe as ran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ing Wolues an empting a new Empire. Gregory</hi> the ninth dyed in deſpaiſe. <hi>Boniface</hi> the eighth dyed of madneſſe. <hi>Paul</hi> the ſecond, hauing yoted as much as euer did <hi>Heſiega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balus</hi>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:3008:43"/>dyed of an Apoplexy. <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt committed Inceſt with his owne daughter, whom alſo he maried to his ſonue,<note place="margin">Paſquil. Natal. comes Hiſt. l. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> and was at the laſt poyſoned by him. <hi>Pius</hi> the fourth dyed in the very boſome of his Concubine. <hi>Paul</hi> the third, when he had waxed old in a filthy courſe of life, dyed, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, my ſinne is alwayes againſt mee. And what ſhould I reckon vp more: whoſo deſireth to read further of them, let him looke into <hi>Pelanus Dan. part</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 467: and <hi>Parker</hi> of the Groſſe, who ſheweth what whores, and <hi>Ganimedes</hi> by name, ſeuerall Popes haue had. <hi>Sergius</hi> had <hi>Marozia. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the ſeuenth, <hi>Matildis. Alexander</hi> the ſixt, <hi>Lucretia:</hi> all their daughters or Siſters. <hi>Sextus</hi> the fourth had for his <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimede Riarius. Iulius</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Germanus. Leo</hi> the tenth, <hi>Hypolitus. Iulius</hi> the third, <hi>Innocentius, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Napier,</hi> who in his expoſition vpon the <hi>Rouelation</hi> reckoneth vp the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of moſt notorious wicked Popes.<note place="margin">Napier Reuel. p. <hi>138.</hi>
                  </note> There haue beene thirteene adulterers: Three common Stewes-haunters: foure inceſtuous perſons: eleuen Sodomiticall perſons: ſeuen ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of Stewes, and two and twenty Necromancers. And <hi>Henricus Echartus,</hi> who in his booke called <hi>Papa Phariſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zans</hi> reckoneth vp the vileſt hereſies, wherwith Popes haue been tainted. Some Sadduces, ſome Montaniſts, Arrians, Neſtorians, Eutychians, and Epicures, and patrons of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>Innocent</hi> 4, defended for gold any luxury in the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie. <hi>Sixtus</hi> 4 gaue liberty of Sodometry to the Cardinals. <hi>Alexander</hi> 4 ſent into England for money, abſolution to all periured and wicked perſons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are theſe things true? is it poſſible, that ſo many monſters ſhould ſit in the Apoſtolike chaire? yet it is true, the office doth not priuiledge from ſinne, alſe</hi> Iudas <hi>being an Apoſtle ſhould not haue been a Deuill, As</hi> Iudas <hi>therefore was no preiudice to the Apoſtolicall office, no more it may bee are ſome wicked Popes to the religion by them maintained. Elſe by the like reaſon the wickedneſſe of ſome of your Biſhops &amp; Miniſters would be an argument againſt your religion.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>For the truth of theſe things I haue alledged my authors; who in theſe ſifting times would not haue written thus, if they could haue been diſproued, And howſoeuer the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:3008:43"/>wickedneſſe of ordinary perſons of the Clergy or Laity can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not miniſter an argument againſt their religion; yet when one, that is aboue all, &amp; as an Oracle, giueth Edicts to all, and guideth the ſhip as he pleaſeth, is noto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iouſly wicked: there needs no greater argument of a wicked religion. Becauſe the religion profeſſed by vs is not founded vpon the Biſhop or Miniſter, but vpon Gods Word; but the religion of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is founded vpon the Pope, ſeeing it is their common Plea, that their Church is founded vpon S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and his ſucceſſors. Such then as the Pope is, ſuch muſt the religion built vpon him needs bee; for ſo much as the building alwayes ſtandeth and falleth with the foundation. It is a ſilly ſhift to ſay, he may erre, as he is a man in manners, but not as Pope in doctrine. For what ground can there be, that the holy Ghoſt will dwell to direct in the truth vpon all occaſions, in a naſty ſty of vncleane ſpirits? For how is the holy Spirit, if not by abominable ſinnes, quenched and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced away? It is a priuiledge of ſuch as feare God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 25.12.</note> to be dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the right; and not of <hi>Balaam,</hi> or <hi>Caiaphas,</hi> though they might ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raordinarily propheſie as <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe ſpake.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elywas.</speaker>
               <p>You muſt not thinke yet to beare vs down thus, as Antichriſtian and abominable in our religion: no, no, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though all were, as you haue ſaid, yet wee want not the ſtrongeſt argument of all, which muſt ſtop all mouths, the very finger of God, which hath often manifeſted it ſelfe, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles wrought at Saints ſepulchres, and images, by exorci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Prieſts to the caſting out of Deuils, by Croſſes, and Holy Water, vvhich haue often put the Deuill to flight; and almoſt all points of our religion haue beene confirmed by miraculous reuelations, to ſome holy perſons of vnſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted credit, who haue vpon their faith affirmed the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe miracles make much on your ſide indeed, to proue your religion Antichriſtian,<note place="margin">Theſ. Reuel.</note> and your Pope Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, ſeeing it is ſaid, that he ſhould come with lying won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and ſhould cauſe fire to come downe from heauen, to theſe ducing of many? Miracles indeed had their vſe in the firſt propagating of the Goſpell:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.</note> but they were for vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, ſmce they haue ceaſed as needleſſe, euen as (to vſe the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:3008:44"/>ſimilitude of <hi>Gregory</hi>) the husbandman hauing newly plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an Orchard, watereth it: But when it is well rooted, hee watereth it no more.<note place="margin">Deut. 23.</note> If any giue a ſigne amongſt the people of God, to proue any new matter in religion, not propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the vvritten Word of God, hee is pronounced a falſe Prophet. Moreouer, many of your miracles haue been proued cooſenages, by which we may gheſſe what the reſt are: and for reuelations, they may well bee counted rather deluſions of Satan, who is ready to tempt men according to their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and ſuperſtitious Monkes to more ſuperſtitions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are miracles then of ſo little force now? What meaneth our Saniour Chriſt when hee maketh this a ſigne of the true faith?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 16.17.</note> He that beleeueth, theſe ſignes ſhall follow, he ſhall caſt out Deuils, lay his hands vpon the ſicke and heale them, &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>Miracles were very frequent indeed then, as was needfull: but it was not to bee expected, that theſe ſignes ſhould follow alwayes, when al countreys and Nations being conuerted, the truth had gotten other ſufficient teſtimonie vvithout ſignes. Onely God doth ſomething miraculouſly oftentimes for the credit of his Goſpell in all ages, as by pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing extraordinarily the enemies of his truth, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſuch as fauour it. Thus the perſecuting Emperors vvere extraordinarily iudged; and the firſt Chriſtian Emperor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily bleſſed, in that they all for the ſpace of three hundred yeares liued moſt turbulent liues, had moſt vnquiet eſtates, and almoſt all of them ſuffered by violent deaths, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſhort raigne: but <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the firſt Chriſtian Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour liued long, was euery where victorious, and then reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in peace, and dyed in peace. And of theſe miracles, bleſſed be God, we are full in this kingdome: for Queene <hi>Mary</hi> that ſtood for Poperie, had but a ſhort time, was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily diſappointed of the hoped for ſucceſſor of her owne body, to the amazement of all, and ſo was cut off in the prime of her age. But Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of bleſſed me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, had a long time, and the diuine protection did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe her about as a ſhield againſt all treaſons, and conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; ſo that they were miraculouſly diſappointed, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:3008:44"/>reigned in peace, inticht her kingdom more then euer, abated the pride of her enemies, and mightily ſuccoured o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſtreſſed Proteſtants, in a good old age ſhe departed in peace. And ſince that time our gracious King, that now raigneth, whom God long preſerue: how miraculouſly both he and we all vnder him haue beene deliuered; and in what peace he hath and doth ſtill gouerne ſuch mighty Nations, like another <hi>Salomon</hi> in ſuch tumultuous times: it is ſo well knowne, that I ſhall not need to ſpeake. And that blow, which your Religion had at Blacke-Friers, October 26 of this yeare, by the onely hand of God, both Teacher and people, to the number of about an hundred perſons, being ſuddenly cut off at one of your Sermons: and the firſt, that hath beene publike to our Country-men, ſince the ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Pope y, and that vpon your Nouember 5, at vvhat time our ouerthrow (thankes bee to God) was in another yeare in vaine attempted: that, I ſay, the like whereof was neuer heard, was a very miracle to the confounding of your ſuperſtitions, which you thought by degrees to bring in here againe, and to crowde out the truth. For howſoeuer we are all to tremble, and to take occaſion to repent by Gods iudgements; yet when <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> with their company, are in the very offering of their incenſe deſtroyed; their ſeruice as a conſpiracy is confounded, that all men may take heed of it, and the ſeruice of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> honoured. I could aſcend higher to times paſt, and ſhew miracles in the fufferings of our Martyrs, and in the iudgements vpon your perſecutors: and I could inlarge my ſelfe to ſpeake of the miraculous preſeruation of <hi>Geneua,</hi> and of the wonderfull ſucceſſe of the Proteſtants in <hi>France</hi> in former times, and of ſome Kings there, and of the <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians</hi> in the time of <hi>Iohn Huſſe:</hi> and it ſhall ſuffice to haue giuen this taſte at home, and ſo neare hand.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elym.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe outward things are no proofes,<note place="margin">Eccl 9.2.</note> ſeeing <hi>all things fall out alike vnto all.</hi> But in the midſt of all your good ſucceſſe, ye haue not been able to inlarge your Religion, but onely to a few countreys here in Europe: whereas the true Church is Catholike ouerſpreading all Nations, which
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:3008:45"/>marke is in the Church of Rome, but not in yours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>You abuſe that Text of all things falling out alike to all. For that is ſpoken only of the godly, and the wicked, which are religious and care not for religion; and not of thoſe that are zealous for their religion, bee it true or falſe, when they are all bound to embrace the truth. For in this caſe God hath euer put a plaine difference betwixt thoſe of his people that haue worſhipped him aright, and that haue beene corrupted by idolatry, powring downe great and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt bleſſings vpon the one ſort, and apparant curſes vpon the other, as it is at large ſet forth in the bookes of <hi>Iudges, Samuel</hi> and the <hi>Kings:</hi> thus as the great Vmpire ouer all, determining for the Truth, and againſt Errour. As for the Catholociſme, which you ſo much bragge of; I haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhewed, that <hi>Grecia</hi> a part of the world not the furtheſt remote, hath neuer wholly imbraced your Religion; and by your cruclties your Church hath become ſo odious amongſt the Indians, that they abhorre it therefore; and it is notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly knowne, that by your very images and faithleſneſſe, the Turkes haue been hindred from ruining to Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ſo haue the ſca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tered Iewes. Our Church is Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, as hath beene proued, and therefore Catholike, though the time is not yet come, ſince the reformation, of being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged to all parts, for ſo neither was Chriſtianitie vpon the ſudden, though caried forth by extraordinary inſtruments. But to yeeld the pretended vniuerſality of your Church ſo corrupted: what tendeth this vnto indeed, but to proue your Church to bee ſpirituall Babel, and your Pope to be the whore of Babel, ſeeing as ſhee, ſo Rome ſitteth as a Queene, and ruleth ouer the Nations of the earth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fie, fie,</hi> Paul, <hi>this ſauoureth rather of ſpleene, then of ſound iudgement: for that Babylon is a perſecuter of all Chriſtians, and an open oppugner of Chriſt, and ſo may with good reaſon indeed bee reputed heathen Rome, vnder the perſecuting Emperours, but not Popiſh Rome, wherein Chriſt is honoured, and Chriſtians are harboured.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>Worthy Sir, I ſpeake out of no ſpleene, but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſedly, pitying the people, that being ſeduced by this
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:3008:45"/>whore, run headlong after her to their own deſtruction. For, that popiſh <hi>Rome</hi> and not heathen <hi>Rome</hi> is that <hi>Babel,</hi> I proue by theſe 2 inuincible reaſons. Firſt, from her name, <hi>the great Whore,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 17.1. verſ. 5.</note> and <hi>the mother of whordomes and abhomiuations of the earth.</hi> Now whordome in the Scripture phraſe, as all know, is Idolatry, and yet euery idolatrous nation is not ſaid to be a whore, but only that where God hath beene rightly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, but his worſhip is become corrupt by the bringing in of Idols: for in this reſpect when <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> are ſaid to haue playd the whore, neither <hi>Babel</hi> nor <hi>Sodom,</hi> nor any other nation is taxed by this name. Whence is neceſſarily followeth, that <hi>Rome</hi> where God hath beene truly worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, but ſince hath beene by Idols corrupted, muſt be meant by <hi>Babel</hi> that great whore; and not heathen <hi>Rome,</hi> which was originally idolatrous. Again, the other part of the name, <hi>the Mother of Whordomes,</hi> implyeth a place, from whence the idolatries of other Countreys haue ſprung, ſuch as was not Heathen <hi>Rome,</hi> which receiued her idolatries from other nations, as ſhe ſubdued them, that they might the more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly obey the Romane State; but Popiſh <hi>Rome,</hi> the very mother of all the Idolatries in all nations round about. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, I reaſon from the end of this <hi>Babel.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel 18 2.</note> Babylon <hi>is falne and is become the habitation of Deuils, the bold of all foule spirits, and a Cage of euery vncleane and hatefull bird.</hi> And againe,<note place="margin">verſ. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>She ſhall be burnt with fire.</hi> Heathen <hi>Rome</hi> falling, this deſolation hath not ſucceeded, but was more worthily inhabited then euer before, with Chriſtians in ſtead of Ethnicks, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this <hi>Babel</hi> is not that <hi>Rome,</hi> but <hi>Rome</hi> that now is, whoſe iudgements ſhall be according to her bleſſings, as the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> not to bee once deſtroyed, and then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peopled againe, but to be burnt with fire, neuer to be againe reedifyed, but to remaine a perpetuall ſpectacle of deſolation for the glory of Gods iuſtice againſt ſuch a ſinke of abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But you haue not yet touched that note, which chiefly is pointed at as the cauſe of</hi> Babels <hi>ruine.</hi> In her was found the blood of the Prophets, and of the Saints,<note place="margin">Reu. 18.24.</note> &amp;c. <hi>What Prophets or Saints haue beene ſlaine in</hi> Rome, <hi>ſince the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:3008:46"/>bare ſway? She hath honoured many Saints with canonizing them, but blood of Saints ſhe hath ſhed none.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>By Prophets, as all know, are vnderſtood Preachers of the Goſpell, and by Saints, godly and faithfull people: for ſuch in the holy Scriptures are called ſaints, the Pope cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized ſaints not being knowne then. And of theſe, what place in the world ſo full of the blood as Popiſh <hi>Rome,</hi> ſith ſhe hath beene the bellows to blow vp the coales, that haue burnt thouſands of moſt godly innocent people, and from her hath been deriued the bloody cruelty which hath been exerciſed by the Potentates of the earth againſt the number<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſhepheards and ſheepe of Chriſts flocke, to the deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them in moſt inhumane and barbarous manner. I thanke you therefore for putting me in minde of this note; for by cruelty and blood-ſhed is the ſinne of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> come to the height, neither doth any thing threaten ſo formidable iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts againſt her as the cry of ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood, ſhed with ſuch exquiſite torments, that if <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar</hi> King of <hi>Babel</hi> were aliue, he might be aſham'd that hee could inuent no more long lingring tormenting death, but caſt thoſe that would not worſhip his Image, into a hot fiery furnace, ſo hot as that they might bee preſently diſpacht, when as the King of this <hi>Babel</hi> hath an hundred wayes more tormenting, to deſtroy his oppugners, and a far more terrifying courſe by impriſoning long, vilely dieting, cruelly racking, and at laſt burning them in a lingring paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>protracting fire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But it is not for their ſanctity, that he dealeth thus with them, but for their Hereſies, for which he thinketh them wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of any torment, that others being by them warned, may take heed of falling into the like.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>This is his pretence indeed, but if it be hereſie, then the pure milke ſucked out of the breſts of the old and new Teſtament without any forraigne mixture muſt be hereſie, for ſuch I haue particularly ſhewed in the beginning of this Colloquy all our doctrine to be. It is therefore for zeale and ſanctity meerly that we ſuffer, and if it were otherwiſe, yet the Pope muſt needs for this be Antichriſt, and popery An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtianiſme.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:3008:46"/>For who is Antichriſt, but he that is againſt Chriſt? and who is againſt Chriſt, but he that teacheth and ſetteth men on to doe againſt Chriſts teaching? If Chriſt then had bidden <hi>Peter</hi> to put vp his ſword and not to ſtrike therewith for his cauſe, in way of reuenge, vpon thoſe that were contrary minded, is not he Antichriſt that gloryeth in ſtriking with the ſword? If Chriſt rebuked the raſh zeale of thoſe that would haue called for fire from heauen to deſtroy ſuch as refuſed to entertaine Chriſt; are not they Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian that with fire &amp; fagot deſtroy all? If Chriſt bad, let the tares and wheat grow together till the harueſt, leſt whileſt the tares be pulled out, the wheat be plucked vp alſo; is not he Antichriſt that biddeth pluck vp the tares howſoeuer, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Hereticks in <hi>France</hi> and in <hi>Germany</hi> by the ſword, and in <hi>England</hi> with Gunpowder, though many Catholikes periſh together with them alſo? To ſay nothing of other things wherein he is plainly againſt Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elym.</speaker>
               <p>You ſhew your ſpite againſt his Holineſſe now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. How can you ſpeake thus without bluſhing, when as it is plainly ſet forth, as the note of Antichriſt,<note place="margin">1. Iohn 4.1.</note> that <hi>he deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Chriſt to haue come in the fleſh:</hi> and <hi>to confeſſe Chriſt come in the fleſh,</hi> the note of Gods Spirit; Wherefore the Pope can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Antichriſt. And if cruelty againſt Heretikes bee an argument to proue Antichriſt, I pray let your rulers take part with him herein; ſeeing that in cruelty they are no whit inferiour to Catholike rulers, if they exceed them not. For what holy Prieſts, and zealous deſmits haue beene ſpared from the ſword, what priuate profeſſors of the Catholike Religion from moſt cruell vſage, impriſoning and ſpoyling ſince the beginning of Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> reigne, cill euen of late, when the clemency of a more mercifull King abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from all tyranny, hath made their yoak ſomwhat eaſier?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>You ſhew eyther your ignorance or wilfulneſſe in alleaging that text of Saint <hi>Iohn.</hi> For who knoweth not, that there are more Antichriſts then one? ſome are open profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed enemies to Chriſt; of whom St. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh, that thoſe may eaſily be knowne by their denying of Chriſt; but there is one called the Antichriſt, which I haue alſo ſet forth, that
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:3008:47"/>
                  <hi>ſitteth in the Temple of God, and commeth with all decei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>able<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> which things could not agree vnto him, if hee plainly denyed Chriſt; and this Antichriſt your Pope may well be, notwithſtanding his outward profeſſion of Chriſtianity. And for your reply to draw in our Gouernors into the ſame predicament for their cruelty. I wonder, that you and your fellowes are not aſhamed to broach ſo many notorious lyes, as you haue done touching all manner of cruelties exerciſed here in <hi>England,</hi> againſt your ſect, when as ſince the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of that moſt bleſſed Queenes reigne (though there was iuſt cauſe, and but your owne meaſure ſhould haue bin meted to you againe, if all your ſect had beene rooted out with fire and ſword without partiality) not one Papiſt hath beene put to death for his religion. But becauſe by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence it was found dangerous to the State, to ſuffer Prieſts and Ieſuits to come into the land, their comming being for treaſon and rebellion, they were proceeded againſt as tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors that preſumed contrary to the Law to enter this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. And leſt there ſhould bee danger in the reſt, they haue beene confined and fined, as commmon policy requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, the more they were kept vnder and reſtrained, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the State being the more; and contrariwiſe the more their wealth and liberty was, the greater was the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Kingdome. Wherefore here hath beene no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of Religion, but of rebellion, no execution done vpon conſcience, but vpon treaſon, as your own conſcience cannot but witneſſe with vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elym.</speaker>
               <p>There is no end, I ſee of wording with you, ſo many are your ſhifts and colours at euery turne: but I hope you haue ſeen your beſt dayes, &amp; both you &amp; your religion ſhall now downe as faſt, as euer it came vp, and the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like religion ſhall be againe in euery place reſtored, and then the deed will proue the truth, and that your hereſy is not of God, for then it could not bee reſiſted. Wherefore (moſt noble Gouernor) let not this Heretick ſeduce you, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for your honor, peace, and ſafety by ioyning with Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Princes, who alone almoſt rule all Europe, and would be glad, to ſee you become a good Catholicke alſo,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:3008:47"/>and ſo to proſecute with all entire loue, honor &amp; eſtimation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
               <p>Now you ſhew your ſelfe in your colours indeed a true child of the Deuill, tempting by worldly honours and reſpects, as he did Chriſt. But (moſt excellent <hi>Sergius</hi>) your wiſedome I hope is ſuch, that you will eaſily reiect theſe temptations as Chriſt did the Deuils, with it is written,<note place="margin">Pſal. 20.8.</note> 
                  <hi>They which truſt in horſes and chariots, or in worldly Princes ſhall fall downe, but ſuch as trust in God ſhall ſtand vp ſtedfaſtly.</hi> For mine owne part I doubt not, but the eager putting on of popiſh Potentates of late dayes to ouerthrow the truth at once, is a preſage of the ruine of that ſuperſtition being e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen at the dores. For ſo the Chriſtian Religion being moſt indangered in the dayes of <hi>Eugenius,</hi> when the aduerſaries ſought to deſtroy it all at once; his rage was turned to bee fatall to Gentiliſme, being immediatly after ſo put downe as that it was neuer able to make head againe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serg. Paul.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>God forbid, that I through any feare or hope ſhould be drawne to that, which I ſo plainly now ſee to bee dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to the ſoule. No, no, (thou bewitching</hi> Elymas) <hi>I haue giuen too much care to thy deceiuable reaſons to incline to ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable an opinion of your Antichriſtianiſme. From henceforth I charge you to come at my Court no more, for I will no more haue communion with you, or ſuch as you are, but onely as I am com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, I will as much as in me</hi> lyeth haue peace with all men. <hi>And thou</hi> Paul, <hi>(the true meſſenger of God) ſhalt at all times be welcome vnto me. Many ſuch Preachers God bleſſe mee and my Dominion with all, for they are truely the ſeruants of God, and all that will be moued the rather for my countenance, let them hearken vnto them, and fly all communion with ſophiſticall Ieſuites and Prieſts: So ſhall I account them good and loyall ſubiects to me in whom my heart ſhall truſt, and they ſhall eſcape the greateſt and the moſt bewitching danger of the ſoule that euer was.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
